<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The XXXVI questions propounded for resolution of unlearned Protestants in matter of religion to the doctors of the prelaticall pretended reformed-Church of England, retorted for resolution on unlearned papists in matter of religion, to V.H. and V.N. doctors of the pretended Catholick Church of Rome / by T. Svvadlin ...</title>
            <author>Swadlin, Thomas, 1600-1670.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 137 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62014</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S6228</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38289</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17287251</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17287251</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106321</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62014)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106321)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1103:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The XXXVI questions propounded for resolution of unlearned Protestants in matter of religion to the doctors of the prelaticall pretended reformed-Church of England, retorted for resolution on unlearned papists in matter of religion, to V.H. and V.N. doctors of the pretended Catholick Church of Rome / by T. Svvadlin ...</title>
                  <author>Swadlin, Thomas, 1600-1670.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 59 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.G. for the use of the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLIX [1659]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, with loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Apologetic works.</term>
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:106321:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106321:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE XXXVI. QUESTIONS <hi>PROPO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NDED</hi> FOR RESOLUTION OF UNLEARNED PROTESTANTS In matter of Religion, to the Doctors of The Prelaticall pretended Reformed-Church of ENGLAND, RETORTED For Reſolution of Unlearned PAPISTS In matter of Religion, to <hi>V. H.</hi> and <hi>V. N.</hi> Doctors of the pretended Catholick Church of ROME.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> T. SVVADLIN, D.D.</p>
            <q>Religio of<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o vera, quae Deo honorabilior, quae paci amicabilior, quae Homini favorabilior.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. G.</hi> for the uſe of the Author, <hi>MDCLIX.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:106321:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:106321:2"/>
            <head>THE XXXVI. QUESTIONS <hi>PROPOUNDED</hi> FOR RESOLUTION OF UNLEARNED <hi>PROTESTANTS, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hether every Chriſtian is not obliged to chuſe the ſafeſt way, all things conſidered,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>1</label> to Salvation?</p>
            <p>Yes Queſtionleſſe;
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> this Queſtion is pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and muſt receive an affirmative An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer; If the reſt prove no worſe, we ſhall not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> long at odds.</p>
            <p>Whether that way wherein both parties acknowledge,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>2</label> that unlearned men may have poſſibility of Salvation, though one of them ſay it be with difficulty and danger, if they look not well to the Foundation, be not prudently to be judged more ſafe for the unlearned, then that which is eſteemed ſafe, by one onely patty, and that incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly leſſe in Number, but by the other incomparably grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter party, which equallizes the leſs in all reſpects requiſite to gain Credit and Authority, is conſtantly held to be utterly voide of all poſſibility of Salvation, even for un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned perſons?</p>
            <p>I wiſh you had not ſo ſoon forgot the piety of your firſt Queſtion; it is not,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>2</label> it cannot be g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nted, that becauſe the incomparably greater party (Authoritatively ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, to take no notice of what follow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Salvation to any of the incomparably leſs number, and that leſs number acknowledge a poſſibility of Salvation to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:106321:3"/>the unlearned of the greater party, it is therefore prudent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be judged more ſafe for the unlearned to make choyce of the greater number, as the ſafeſt way to Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>For firſt, the incomparably greater number is a Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude; and therefore not the ſafeſt way to follow them.</p>
            <p>For ſecondly, the incomparably greater number, may with the incomparably conceited Crowes, think their own feathers whiteſt.</p>
            <p>For thirdly, your Argument thus retorts upon your ſelf; the incomparably greater number, and the incomparably leſs number, both confeſs Scripture to be infallible; but the leſs deny the <hi>Pope</hi> to be infallible.</p>
            <p>The like is confeſt of Faith to be a ſure rule; Tradition is denyed by one.</p>
            <p>The old Creedes both grant, a new one is denyed by us.</p>
            <p>To worſhip God is confeſt by both; but to worſhip Images, or God by Images is denyed by us.</p>
            <p>To truſt in Chriſts Merits is confeſt by both; but to truſt in Mans own Merits is denyed by us.</p>
            <p>To pray to God in Chriſts Name is confeſt by both; but to pray to Saints, or to God in the Name of Saints is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed by us.</p>
            <p>In the Sacrament of the Euchariſt is confeſt by both, a Sacrifice Commemorative, but a propitiatory Sacrifice is denyed by us.</p>
            <p>A reall preſence we both grant; but a Carnall we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.</p>
            <p>The Body and Blood by Inſtitution, and Primitive Obſervation we both acknowledge, but an Alienation of the Cup we diſclaim.</p>
            <p>In the Engliſh Liturgy is no error ſay ſome of you; in the <hi>Roman Miſſall</hi> are many, ſay all of us; and therefore by this Argument of yours, it is by prudence to be judged more ſafe for the unlearned to chuſe that way to Salvation, which is confeſt by both, then that which is conceived ſafe by one party onely, <hi>i.e.</hi> yours.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:106321:3"/>
            <p>I have been ſomewhat long upon this, and yet muſt be a little longer, becauſe of your Marginall Note <hi>(viz.) Biſhop.</hi> of <hi>Cant. Sect.</hi> 35. <hi>p.</hi> 280. Whom you quote ſomewhat erroniouſly; for he bids, <hi>Marke, it is but a poſſibility of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,</hi> he grants to ſilly ſouls in the Romiſh Church; but a ſecure way he denies you, and he backs it from St. <hi>Auguſtine, Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de Bapt. cont. Don. ca.</hi> 3. Who judged it a great ſin to prefer, <hi>Incerta certis</hi> uncertaine, and naked poſſibilities before an evident and certain courſe: And there he gives you a taſte too from your own Learned Card. <hi>Bellar. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>de, Juſtif. ca.</hi> 7. <hi>Tutiſſimum eſt,</hi> and afterwards layes you, and the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> together in this want of Charity amongſt you, or <hi>Charity miſtaken</hi> by you, and laſtly deſires you that you would not make us as malicious (at leaſt as raſh) as your ſelves, in deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Salvation to ſome ignorant ſilly ſouls, whoſe humble and peaceable obedience makes them ſafe among any part of men, that profeſs the Foundation <hi>Chriſt,</hi> let him that pleaſeth read the whole thirty five Section, and he will ſoon reſolve which is the ſafer way, yours or ours.</p>
            <p>Whether this be not the preſent Caſe betwixt <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants,</hi> and thoſe of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>3</label> according to the acknowledgment of the lateſt and learnedeſt of <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant</hi> Authors; Biſhop of <hi>Cant. ibid.</hi> They acknowledge the ſaid poſſibility of Salvation for unlearned perſons in the <hi>Roman,</hi> and the <hi>Roman</hi> Doctors denying all poſſibility to unlearned <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> ſo long as they remaine wilfully in the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion.</p>
            <p>Let it be the preſent Caſe betwixt us,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>3</label> ſo you take the Reſtriction of the lateſt, and learned'ſt <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Authors, and particularly of that moſt Reverend Father in God, and now with God, becauſe his Martyr, and ſumme up your gaines; There is a poſſibility, and but a poſſibility of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation for unlearned <hi>Papiſts</hi> in the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> which argues our Charity; There is no poſſibility for Learned or unlearned <hi>Protestants,</hi> ſay you, which argues your malice, <hi>Cant.</hi> p. 285. Yes, which likens, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares you with the <hi>Donatiſts;</hi> The words of the ſame
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:106321:4"/>Archbiſhop: Who galls you thus; whether the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Baptiſme was true in the Catholick Church, or in the part of <hi>Donatus;</hi> The <hi>Donatiſts</hi> exhorted all to be Baptized amongſt them; why? Becauſe both parties granted that Baptiſme was true amongſt the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> which that peeviſh ſect moſt unjuſtly denyed the ſound part, as St. <hi>Auguſtine, lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Cont. Don. de Baptiſt. ca.</hi> 3. delivers it. I would aske now (the Archbiſhops own words) had not the Orthodox true Baptiſme among them, becauſe the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> denyed it injuriouſly? Now I ſay, pray read the Archbiſhop on, and put the truth into your eyes, and tell the world if you ſee ere the worſe.</p>
            <p>Whether all unlearned <hi>Proteſtants,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>4</label> who are ſufficiently informed of what is hereſaid are not guilty of a damnable neglect of their Salvation, ſo long as they remaine <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants,</hi> and refuſe to be of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church?</p>
            <p>And why not Learned as well as unlearned?
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>4</label> certain <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> they would be in the deeper guilt, if there were any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ther; becauſe Vivacity of Underſtanding ſtriving <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> his own Light, makes more guilty then ſimplicity of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ving can poſſibly do, ſo poſſibility of Salvation for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple man in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church there is; but for a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> man, one that knowes the errors of the Church, (and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> know a great many) there is not, for ought I yet know, ſo much as a poſſibility: Yet a little more from that moſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Archbiſhop whom you have cited twice before; my ſoul for a ſimple peaceable believing ſoul in the Church of <hi>England;</hi> not ſo for ſuch an one in the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> no more for him or her but a poſſibility.</p>
            <p>Whether a perſon who is in quiet poſſeſſion of any Goods,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>5</label> Tythes, Titles, Rights or Dignities, &amp;c. retaine not the Right to all ſuch Goods, and is wrongfully deprived of them, ſo long as he neither confeſſes that he hath no Right to them, nor is condemn'd by the clear ſentence of any lawfull or competent Judge of ſufficient Authority to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſine againſt him, but ſtill maintaines his Cauſe againſt his Adverſary, and gives at leaſt probable Anſwers to all that he alleadgeth againſt him, and pleads to be reſtored to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:106321:4"/>his ancient poſſeſſion, taken from him by force and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and whether he who thus violently took the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion from him, be not obliged in Conſcience to reſtore it to him again? And whether he proceeds not unjuſtly ſo long as he retaines it from him?</p>
            <p>I ſhall anſwer this impertinent Queſtion by retorting it with a ſimile more veriſimilitude like.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>5</label> 
            </p>
            <p>Whether if a Biſhop, (the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> be the man) do wrongfully deprive the Emperour (Emperour of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many</hi> be he) of his-Rights and Dignities, in calling Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Councils, claiming his Right to that particular, and uncondemn'd by the clear ſentence of any lawfull and competent Judge, &amp;c. (pardon that Sir,) I but follow your own example in this very Paragraph) doth not ſin egregiouſly in this detenſion? Will you have another? Thus, whether if a Thief by force get in poſſeſſion of your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and goods, be not ſtill a Thief, ſo long as he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> them; and your ſelf a Fool, if you lay not hold <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the firſt opportunity to reſume them? This is our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> though it ſeemeth yours, your Church the Church <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Rome,</hi> or rather the Biſhop, and Court of <hi>Rome</hi> had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>oched, and uſurped too far upon the Rights of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which was alwaies oppoſed, but at laſt regained, though now (for our ſins, or by the ſins of others) diſpoſed a third way, but it was violent, and I hope will not be laſting.</p>
            <p>Whether th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> hath not been within the laſt hundred and fifty yeares, and ſtill is,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>6</label> the proceeding of <hi>Proteſtants</hi> againſt the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, violently excluding her Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Paſtors, and People, from the quiet poſſeſſion of many hundred yeares continuance of their Doctrine, Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, Titles, Governments, Benefices, Churches, Poſſeſſions, and ſtill retaine them, and refuſing to reſtore them, thoſe of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church ſtill claiming their Right, and never having been condemn'd by any compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, or lawfull Judge, nor acknowledging themſelves convinced to have obtained that poſſeſſion wrongful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly?</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:106321:5"/>
            <p>Sir,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>6</label> part of this is true, and part of this is falſe; That them whom you call <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> (<hi>Catholicks</hi> I ſhould have called them) have thus dealt with them of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church for, 150. yeares ſhall not be denyed by me, nor will it be denyed by you that they did it juſtly; becauſe the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> had never any univerſall power, untill an uſurping Pope, <hi>Boniface</hi> by name, from an uſurping Emperour <hi>Phoras,</hi> who murthered his Maſter <hi>Mauritius,</hi> gave him the Title of Univerſall Biſhop, and for their robbing the Engliſh Church betwixt 600. and 700. yeares, the Engliſh Church, and Churchmen with the conſent of King and Parlament, have reſumed their own; which whether you will acknowledg to be a competent and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Judge, and your ſelves convinced to have obtained your former poſſeſſions wrongfully, I ſhall leave to wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer men, then you, or my ſelf to determine.</p>
            <p>Whether the quiet poſſeſſion of many Ages,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>7</label> both of the Eaſterne, and Weſterne Churches, in their una<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous conſent of Doctrine, and Practiſe, in moſt points o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Controverſie betwixt them and <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> be not a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient proof to juſtifie the ſaid Doctrine and Practiſe, till it be convinced clearly, evidently and undeniably, (by Reaſon, or Authority) or lawfully condemned of Error? So that it belongs to <hi>Proteſtants</hi> who are the Aggreſſors, to convince their Adverſaries of Error, and not to thoſe of the <hi>Romane,</hi> or <hi>Grecian</hi> Churches, to prove their Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents by any other Arguments, then that of their quiet, antient, and univerſall poſſeſſion, though <hi>Catholicks</hi> be upon the Affirmative, and <hi>Proteſtauts</hi> upon the Negative; as he who quietly poſſeſſes the Name, Title, Armes and Lands, of ſuch, and ſuch a family, hath ſufficiently proved, that he hath a Right to them, and that they are truly his, till he either confeſſe, that the contrary is ſufficiently proved, or that it be lawfully determined againſt him?</p>
            <p>It is confeſt,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>7</label> that the unanimous conſent of Doctrine and Practiſe of the Eaſterne and Weſterne Churches, in all points of Doctrine betwixt them and <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> would prove ſome thing of ſufficiency; but in moſt points, it
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:106321:5"/>riſeth not to a ſufficient proof; and yet for your <hi>moſt points</hi> you leap before you look; for if you look upon the Rites in Baptiſme, you agree not with the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Church, we do; nor do you agree with them any more then we do in the point of the <hi>Proceſſion of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> nor do they any more yield to you in the Infallibility, and Supremacy of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome;</hi> ſo that the conſent of the <hi>Eaſtern,</hi> or <hi>Grecian,</hi> and the <hi>Western</hi> or <hi>Roman,</hi> is not unanimous in moſt, much leſs in all points of Controverſies againſt the <hi>Proteſtants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whether is it not a moſt inſolent madneſs (as St.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>8</label> 
               <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> termes it) or an inſufferable height of pride, for any Chriſtian whatſoever, to call in Queſtion, much more to cenſure and condemne as erroneous, that which all the viſible Churches in the World taught and Practiſed, and a manifeſt foolery to follow any Teachers, and give eare and belief to them, who contradict the univerſall Practiſe and Doctrine of the whole Chriſtian World?</p>
            <p>Sir,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>8</label> had not theſe words been ſpoken in relation to them, whom you call <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and we call <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks</hi> (for the <hi>Romans</hi> and <hi>Catholicks</hi> are not Termes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertible) or had theſe words been ſpoken as St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpake them, in relation to the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> plain <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks,</hi> and ſo condemned, which <hi>Proteſtants</hi> were never yet lawfully condemned to be, theſe words of youre might have paſſed, and therefore for hereafter good words I pray; elſe your <hi>inſolent madneſſe,</hi> may make mad-men ſober; your <hi>inſufferable height of pride,</hi> may make proud-men humble; and your <hi>manifeſt foolery,</hi> may make fooles ſo wiſe, as not longer o follow ſuch Teachers as your ſelves, who for many hundred yeares have contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted the univerſall Practiſe and Doctrine of the whole Chriſtian World, <hi>Eaſtern</hi> and <hi>Weſtern;</hi> prove you new <hi>Rome</hi> challenges no more priviledges then old <hi>Rome</hi> did, a <hi>Patriarchat-ſhip,</hi> and no more, prove that <hi>Patriarchall power</hi> above the <hi>Supreme Eccleſiaſticall power,</hi> a Generall Council, to which Patriarchall was alwaies ſubject; prove us convinced by either, you ſay ſomething; till
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:106321:6"/>then, I ſtir not farther in theſe dirty words.</p>
            <p>Whether the firſt was not done by the firſt Authors of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>9</label> and the ſecond done, and ſtill continued by their followers? Or if the firſt Authors of <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> received thoſe points of their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine from any <hi>viſible Church</hi> in the whole World, which exiſted immediately before their relinquiſhing the <hi>Roman</hi> Doctrine, let that <hi>Church</hi> be produced and named.</p>
            <p>Sir,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>9</label> this Queſtion deſires another Queſtion for anſwer; what do you mean, by <hi>whether the firſt was not done by the firſt Authors of the Proteſtant Religion?</hi> If you mean <hi>inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent madneſſe, inſufferable height of pride,</hi> for any Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an whatſoever, to call in queſtion, much more to cenſure and condemn as erroneous, that which all the viſible Churches in the World taught and Practiſed? With your good leave, you muſt name the firſt Authors, and what it was they cenſured and condemned, and ſo you muſt explain what followes, and the ſecond done, and ſtill continued by <hi>their followers:</hi> if you meane manifeſt foolery to follow any Teachers, and to give eare and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief to them, who contradict the univerſall Practiſe and Doctrine of the whole Chriſtian World; You muſt name that univerſall Doctrine and Practiſe of the whole Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian World, and how we have contradicted it, elſe you fight with the wind, and ſay nothing.</p>
            <p>For the reſt of this ninth Queſtion, <hi>to produce and name that viſible Church,</hi> from whence we have received thoſe points of Doctrine, which exiſted immediately before we relinquiſhed the <hi>Roman</hi> Doctrine, the <hi>Roman Church</hi> it ſelf is named, and named <hi>thus,</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>Antiquam Romam non Anglia, Roma reliquit,</l>
                  <l>Anglia non Romam Britannes Roma repellit,</l>
               </q> Do but return to the old <hi>Roman</hi> Doctrine in the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive and Catholick Conſtitution of it, and we are friends, till then, Farewell.</p>
            <p>Seeing <hi>Proteſtants</hi> affirm,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>10</label> that the <hi>Roman</hi> Church is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:106321:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>with errors in faith, which they pretend to have purged in their Reformation, I demand that it be eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, when any of thoſe pretended errors began to be pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly taught, and Practiſed out of ſome approved Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of any Age, who affirm, that the publick profeſſion of the ſaid errors, begun in, or about their times; for ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they were publickly Practiſed through all Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, if that publick Practiſe had ever begun in any Age ſince the Apoſtles, it muſt have been taken notice of, whereby their inſtances of Conſumption of the Lungs, of a beard growing white, &amp;c. are ſhewed to be nothing to the purpoſe, becauſe they are either wholly ſecret, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible, and no way publick or notorious, as theſe were; and ſeeing faith by St. <hi>Paul, Eph.</hi> 4. <hi>v.</hi> 1, 3. <hi>is ſaid to be one,</hi> and reckoned up with the Unity of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and ſo muſt be perfectly <hi>one,</hi> how <hi>Proteſtants</hi> and thoſe of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church be properly ſaid to have <hi>one Faith,</hi> when the one believes, what the other disbelieves? And as opinions contradicting one another cannot be ſaid to be one opinion, how can Faiths contradicting one another be ſaid to be one Faith? Neither is it enough to ſay, that they are one in that, wherein they agree, for ſo they will be one onely in part, or partially, and not abſolutely and entirely, and as the leaſt difference deſtroys the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Unity of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſo will it do that of Faith; and though my opinion agree with that of another in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things, but diſagrees in many other from his; we can never be ſaid abſolutely (as it muſt be in Faith,) to be of the ſame, and one opinion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doloſus verſatur <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ca univerſalibus,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>10</label> your arguing by univerſalls, and yet requiring particular anſwers, argues you to be deceiptfull, and to ſeek for Triumph, more then Truth; yet that people may be undeceived, I ſhall fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low your univerſalls with my particulars; and though I could pay you with your own coyne, in ſaying while the good man ſlept, the en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ous man ſowed Tares, yet I pay you in more current coyne, and ſay, <hi>Proteſtants</hi> affirm not, that the <hi>Roman</hi> Church is infected with errors in Faith,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:106321:7"/>and yet we ſay, there are manifeſt and clear errors in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, which we purged, and when ſome of your Errors (not pretended but reall Errors) begun thus is evidenced. Purgatory was never publickly taught by the whole Chriſtian Church, and never decreed by the <hi>Roman</hi> Church it ſelf, untill the <hi>Elorentine</hi> Council, 1439.</p>
            <p>Tranſubſtantiation was never publickly taught by the whole Chriſtian Church, nor allowed or decreed by the <hi>Roman</hi> Church it ſelf, untill the <hi>Laterane</hi> Council, 1215.</p>
            <p>Worſhipping of Images was never publickly taught, nor allowed or decreed, untill the ſecond <hi>Nicene</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, 787.</p>
            <p>Communion in one kind not above 200. yeares, Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy of the <hi>Pope</hi> was condemned by St. <hi>Gregory</hi> himſelf, <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Ep.</hi> 16. <hi>Anno</hi> 600. for Antichriſtian.</p>
            <p>For your Conſumption in the Lungs, and a Beard grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing white, I think with you, they are nothing to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, whether yours, or ours; nor is it to my purpoſe to be ſatisfied with the colour of your Beard, whether it be blew or yellow.</p>
            <p>To your Text of St. <hi>Paul, Eph.</hi> 4. <hi>v.</hi> 1, 2. I confeſſe <hi>Faith is ſaid to be one,</hi> and believe you believe, that you of the <hi>Roman,</hi> and we of the Engliſh Church, have both but one Faith; whether you take it for the Rule of Faith, the Creed; If you have a new Creed, we leave you; or the end of Faith, Salvation, if you have any other end<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> we leave you; or the meanes of that Faith, and Salvation, <hi>Chriſt;</hi> If you have any other means, we leave you ſtill, and for your contradicting opinions, I tell you, it is a lame ſimilitude to bring in thereby contradicting Faith; for though you and I agree but partially in points of opinion, yet we agree entirely in point of Faith.</p>
            <p>Whether it be not a great Argument,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>11</label> to induce any rationall indifferent man to judge that the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors are put to great ſtraits, and to deſperate acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgments; which being aſhamed of the firſt refuge of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:106321:7"/>their beginners, in dying for the defence of their ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to an inviſible Church, in alleadging for their Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, and continuance of the viſibility of their Church, <hi>Berengarius,</hi> the <hi>Waldenſes, Albigerſes, Wicklifſts, Huſſits,</hi> and other publickly condemned <hi>Hereticks,</hi> they confeſſe now that they have no other means to ſave their viſible Succeſſion, but by acknowledging, that they ſucceed to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and other Churches adjoyning with her againſt them, in all the points of difference betwixt them and her, and all thoſe who are united to her, to be true Churches of Chriſt, and conſequently to hold no fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall Error at all; and conſequent to this, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that their firſt Authors, and Churches both in <hi>England</hi> and other Countries, wronged the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and thoſe others inſufferably, firſt, in condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning them of Superſtition, Idolatry, Antichriſtianiſme, &amp;c. Which are fundamentall Errors in Religion, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive of Salvation.</p>
            <p>Secondly, upon this pretext in deſtroying, burning, and alienating to ſecular uſes, ſo many thouſands of their Churches, Monaſteries, Townes, Cities, Caſtles, Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lages.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, in Maſſacrating, and putting to cruell Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and death ſo many Prieſts and Profeſſors of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Religion.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, in depriving their Biſhops and Clergymen of their reſpective Church-Governments, Dignities, Seas, Benefices and Churches, and ſetting up others, they get livings in their places.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, in making it no leſs then High-Treaſon (which is yet in force) either to be Prieſts, or to communicate with them in many Spirituall Church-Offices and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, in continuing to this day, in a violent detaining of their Churches, Benefices, Dignities, and Spirituall Functions, from all thoſe of the <hi>Ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an</hi> profeſſion, and holding them in their own hands; and all this becauſe they maintain certain pretended Errors, which they now
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:106321:8"/>confeſs not to be fundamentall, nor deſtructive of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and conſequently that thoſe of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church have ſuffered, and ſtill ſuffer all theſe intollerable injuries, for that which even theſe Modern Authors acknowledg to be no more then a venial and ſmall ſin; for if it were mortall, it would deſtroy Salvation, ſo long as one wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully continues in it, which they affirm it does not.</p>
            <p>Further by this Acknowledgement, theſe modern <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant</hi> Authors muſt confeſs, that their former Writers, who were of a contrary mind, in charging the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the reſt with her, of Superſtition and Idolatry, &amp;c. and all thoſe who then joyned with them, and all their modern Churches and <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> both without and within <hi>England,</hi> who at this day hold it a point of their Faith to accuſe the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in the ſame manner<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> erre damnably againſt Chriſtian Truth, and ſo conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently are no true Churches of Chriſt; for it cannot be leſs then a damnable Error, to make it a point of their Faith and Religion to condemn any one, much more all the viſible Churches of the <hi>Weſt,</hi> nay and of the <hi>East</hi> too, and ſo of whole Chriſtendom, for nine hundred yeares to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether of grievous Superſtition, when upon better exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, the Doctors of the ſame <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Church, are compelled by force of truth to confeſs, that thoſe Churches neither are, nor ever were guilty of thoſe horrid Errors, and at moſt erre onely venially and lightly, which hinder them not either to be a true Church of Chriſt, or to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Salvation, (Biſhop of <hi>Cant. p.</hi> 129. <hi>num.</hi> 3.) Even while they conſtantly and immoveably maintain them, and accuſe all, who wilfully contradict them, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn them as erroneous. And hence alſo it follows, that ſeeing theſe modern <hi>Protestant</hi> Authors and their party Communicate in Prayer and Sacraments with the <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians</hi> and <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> who accuſe the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> of Idolatry, &amp;c. (and ſo put it in fundamentall error) and acknowledg themſelves to make one Church with them, muſt be guilty of deadly Schiſme by that Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and acknowledgment; and conſequently ſo long
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:106321:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>as they continue in that Communion are uncapable of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
            <p>Here are many words to ſmall purpoſe,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>11</label> a Queſtion might have been couched in five lines, enlarged to five pages; my anſwer muſt be anſwerable.</p>
            <p>Know you therefore whoſoever you are without a name; <hi>Proteſtants</hi> are not put to great ſtraits, nor deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate acknowledgments, they are not aſhamed of their firſt beginners. They ſtand not for the Succeſſion of an invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Church; they acknowledg not for their firſt begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of a viſible Church <hi>Berengarius,</hi> the <hi>Waldenſes, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bigenſes, Wicklifſts, Huſſits,</hi> (whom yet you cannot truly affirm to have been legally condemned for Hereticks) but we alleadge for our Predeceſſors <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his Apoſtles, <hi>Ignatius, Clemens, Hegeſippus, Polycarpus, Irenaeus, Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philus, Tertullian, Cyprian, Origan, Methodius, Gregory, Neozes, Conſtantius Magnus, Euſebius Caſarian, La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctantius, Athanaſius, Hilarius, Baſilius Magnus, Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius, Nyſſenus, Gregorius Nazianzenus, Hieronymus, Epiphanius, Ambrotius, Chryſoſtomus, Cyrillus, Theodore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, Auguſtinus,</hi> with the foure <hi>Oecumenicall Councils</hi> of <hi>Nice,</hi> of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> of <hi>Calcedon,</hi> with all the holy company of <hi>Saints,</hi> and noble Army of <hi>Martyrs,</hi> untill the ſeventh Age, againſt whoſe poſitions if we hold any thing, name it, we anſwer it; prove it, we yeild; and many more Catholicks ſince, we acknowledge not to ſucceed the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> we were and are as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> was of the Catholick Church; we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge her to be a true Church, we deny her to be the true Church: ſhe is, and we are parts of the true Church, yet we not ſo erroneous as ſhe; we acknowledge not to have wronged the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> we complain that the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> or rather the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> with his Court, hath wronged that Church, this Church, and with both the whole <hi>Chatholick Church</hi> by Quittance, and by Forfeiture.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By Quittance, the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> hath wronged the Church, in aſſuming to himſelf the Title of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſall
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:106321:9"/>Biſhop,</hi> and <hi>ſpirituall Soveraigne,</hi> and Monarch of the Church, which is as inconſiſtent with a <hi>Provinciall Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archiat-ſhip</hi> (which was never by any, nor ſhall by me be denyed him) as Humane and Divine Inſtitution.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By Forfeiture, for if the Rebellion of an Inferior for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feits by renouncing his Loyalty to his Superiour, then the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> is notorious in his Rebellion againſt <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Councils,</hi> the onely Supreme Eccleſiaſticall power; and not onely againſt a <hi>Generall Council,</hi> the Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church, but alſo againſt the Catholick Church, in uſurping a Dominion over it.</p>
            <p>And not onely by Rebellion, but alſo by Robbery; who but the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> would have robbed the King of <hi>England</hi> of his Inveſtitures of Biſhops; which <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh proteſted againſt by his Proctour? Who but the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> robbed the King of his Patronages, by Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, Proviſions and Expectative Graces? Who but he robbed the King of <hi>England</hi> of the laſt Appeales of his Subjects contray to the ancient Lawes of <hi>England?</hi> I could go on to inferior Robberies committed by the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> upon the Nobility and Clergy of <hi>England,</hi> but I haſten to the reſt of your Queſtion.</p>
            <p>We have not condemned your Church of <hi>Rome</hi> of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, Idolatry, Antichriſtianiſme, &amp;c. Private men it may be have, the Church of <hi>England</hi> have not; and if the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> be guilty of ſuch Errors, let her free her ſelf.</p>
            <p>The Church of <hi>England</hi> hath not deſtroved, burnt, alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated to ſecular uſes, thouſands of your Churches, Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, Townes, Citties, Villages; if any ſuch things have been done, let the Actors be queſſtioned, let not the Church of <hi>England</hi> be blamed.</p>
            <p>The Church of <hi>England</hi> hath not put to cruell Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and death many Prieſts and Profeſſors of the <hi>Roman</hi> Religion, nor deprieved their Biſhops and Clergy of their Church-Governments; the Church of <hi>England</hi> hath onely recovered their own; the Church of <hi>England</hi> hath not made it High Treaſon to be Prieſts; you know, when they
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:106321:9"/>are executed, they executed for ſomething elſe, then for being Prieſts.</p>
            <p>The Church of <hi>England</hi> continues not in a violent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of <hi>Roman</hi> Benefices, but in a lawfull poſſeſſion of their own; and all this, not for certain <hi>pretended</hi> but <hi>reall</hi> Errors, which you of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church do hold, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to Salvation to ſuch knowing men as your ſelf, though not of the ſame conſequence to ſimple and well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaning men amongſt you; the diſtinction of your <hi>veni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Sins,</hi> we refer to your ſelves; every ſin we ſay is <hi>mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall,</hi> ſo long as a man wilfully continues in it, knowing it to be ſin.</p>
            <p>Nor do we hold it a point of Faith, to accuſe the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> of Superſtition, and Idolatry; but if you are guilty of ſuch Crimes, look you to it; we erre not damnably in ſaying, Worſhipping Images, or God by Images, is Idolatry, and therefore for all this, are true Churches of Chriſt; we condemn not the viſible Churches of the <hi>Weſt,</hi> nor of the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> much leſs, whole Chriſtendom for 900. yeares together of Superſtition; name but one point, we hold contrary to the Tenents of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church for 1600. yeares, (I give you a larger time) we yield.</p>
            <p>You are come acain to erring venially and lightly, to which you had anſwer before; onely take this by way of addition to your Quotation of the Biſhop of <hi>Cant. p.</hi> 129. <hi>Num.</hi> 3. All that that Learned and moſt Reverend Biſhop ſaies, and grants, is, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is a true Church in Effence, and this, becauſe ſhe receiveth the Scripture as a Rule of Faith, though as but a partiall and imperfect Rule, and both the Sacraments as Inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Cauſes and Seales of Grace, though they adde more and miſuſe theſe: And now what you have got by this Quotation, when you have underſtood it, you may alter to a better Mode.</p>
            <p>To your laſt which charges us to Communicate in Prayer and Sacraments with the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> and <hi>Calvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts,</hi> and ſo are guilty of deadly <hi>Schiſme,</hi> and are thereby
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:106321:10"/>conſequently uncapable of Salvation, I would and do wiſh you had not ſpoke falſe Engliſh, for we Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate neither with <hi>Presbyterian</hi> or <hi>Calviniſt,</hi> let them be all one, it is all one to me, they are at a greater dinance from us then <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf. And I think the poor Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> ſuffers more under one of them, then ever ſhe did under the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> and therefore as yet are as capable of Salvation, as you of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we hold of the Catholick, in which, and which Church onely is Salvation; and from which Church if you have made a Schiſme, by giving the cauſe of ſeparation, let it be your care to return to the Catholick, that we may ſhake hands and be friends.</p>
            <p>Whether it be not a great Argument of ſecurity to thoſe who either are of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church or convert them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to it,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>12</label> that her very Adverſaries after ſo many con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnations of her to hold moſt grievous and damnable Errors, dare not now accuſe her to hold any Error de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive of Salvation; ſo that the belief of her Doctrine in every point, their obedience to all her Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the exerciſe of all her Practiſes, their praying to Saints, reverencing of holy Images, adoring of Chriſt, as really and naturally preſent in the Sacrament, &amp;c. conſiſt with Salvation: And though ſome ſay, Biſhop of <hi>Cant. p.</hi> 281. though theſe deſtroy not Salvation, yet they are dangerous points and Practiſes, weakning the Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and endeavouring the deſtruction of it in continuance of time; yet who ſees not that it is more ſecure to hold a Religion which makes the Foundation onely weak, by their Adverſaries conceſſion, then to hold theirs, which the contrary party moſt conſtantly affirms to deſtroy quite, and raſe the Foundation of Religion, and to make Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, not onely hard and in danger, but utterly impoſſible, till it be deſerted.</p>
            <p>Security it may be,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>12</label> not a ſafe ſecurity; for certainly, praying to Saints, which hath neither Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, Pattern, nor Promiſe, Reverencing of holy Images, which hath a direct prohibition, if they are not holy, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:106321:10"/>how they are made holy, you ſhould do well to tell us; adoring Chriſt as really and naturally preſent in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, if by naturally preſent you underſtand carnally, which hath a direct negation in the Scriptures, will not conſiſt with ſalvation, no not with a poſſibility of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; which you might have learnt from the Archbiſhop of <hi>Cant.</hi> if you had Quoted him right; for in the 181. <hi>p.</hi> which you cite, not a word of any ſuch thing. But in the 281. and 282. it is to the purpoſe, not yours but ours; and there you ſhall find thus much with much more; a ſecure way they cannot go, that <hi>hold with ſuch Corruptions when they know them; now whether it be wiſdom in ſuch a point as Salvation is, to forſake a Church in the which the ground of Salvation is firm, to follow a Church in which it is but poſſible one may be ſaved, but very probably he may do worſe, if he look not well to the Foundation, judge ye.</hi> So the Archbiſhop, ſo I, and ſo you have an anſwer to your 12. Queſtion.</p>
            <p>Whether it be a likely thing,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>13</label> that the chiefeſt of the pretended Errors in the <hi>Roman</hi> Religion, contain any dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of loſing Salvation in maintaining them, ſeeing for this 1000 yeares by the common confeſſion of <hi>Proteſtants</hi> themſelves, they have been univerſally believed and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed as matters belonging to Chriſtian Faith and Duty, both by the Latine and Greek Church; and in the belief and Practiſe of them was the common way wherein Chriſtians were ſaved, which if it were dangerous, what other ſafe way was there wherein Chriſtians might be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved? and yet certainly there was alwaies a ſafe way to Heaven. And what likelihood is there that the ſafe way ſhould be wholly unknown, and unpractiſed for ſo many hundred yeares together, and the common known way according to the full belief, and ſetled perſwaſion of all the viſible Churches of Chriſtendom ſhould be dangerous and unſafe? Or what reaſon can be given, that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of the Doctrine of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church ſhould be in an unſafe and dangerous way, before <hi>Proteſtants</hi> began, ſeeing they had none in thoſe times, to ſhew them that they were in danger?</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:106321:11"/>
            <p>Yes,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>13</label> likely enough, for the chiefeſt of the Errors (not pretended, but Errors) in the <hi>Roman</hi> Religion, contain danger of loſing Salvation in maintaining them, elſe why did <hi>Bellarmine</hi> himſelf (the greateſt and learned'ſt Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ever had,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 5. <hi>de Juſt. c.</hi> 7.</note>) <hi>ſay in regard of the uncertainty of our own Righteouſneſs, and of the danger of vaine-glory, it is ſafeſt to repoſe our whole truſt in the mercy and goodneſſe of God.</hi> And I think, and you believe, this is one Error, which contains Error of loſing Salvation; for he that ſtands upon his own Merits totally or partially, is very like to come ſhort of Salvation: Elſe King <hi>David</hi> would never have prayed, <hi>Enter not into judgement with thy Servant O Lord, for no fleſh is righteous in thy ſight:</hi> Elſe the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> would never have ſaid, <hi>our Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe is as a filthy cloath:</hi> Elſe Chriſt would never have Commanded us to confeſs, <hi>when we have done all we can,</hi> to ſay, <hi>we are unprofitable Servants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seeing for 1000. yeares, by the common conſent of <hi>Proteſtants</hi> themſelves, they have been univerſally belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and Practiſed.</p>
            <p>It is not long ſince you ſaid for 900. yeares, now a thouſand; but to let that paſs, for it is but 100. yeares diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and we can well afford it you, ſince it is ſaid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain as before, prove any point that the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> holds was not the univerſall Doctrine of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church for 900. yes, 1600. yeares, and then it ſhall be confeſt, you have ſaid ſomething, and therefore no dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger yet, but Chriſtians were ſaved in and by the right way, but not in and by the <hi>Roman</hi> way, as the <hi>Roman</hi> way is now.</p>
            <p>And yet more; you had ſome that did tell you, that the preſent <hi>Roman</hi> way was not, is not a ſafe way to Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; what elſe perſwaded St. <hi>Bernard</hi> to deny praying to Saints? What elſe before him, put <hi>Gelaſius</hi> to ſay, taking the Cup from the <hi>Laity</hi> cannot be done without grand Sacriledge? What elſe after both, put <hi>Gerſon</hi> to give this ſage advice, I ſee that the Reformation of the Church, will never be effected by a Council, without the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:106321:11"/>Preſidence of a well-affected, wiſe and conſtant guide? Let the members therefore provide for themſelves throughout the Kingdoms and Provinces, when they ſhall be able, and know how to compaſs this work.</p>
            <p>What elſe made <hi>Robert de Groſteſte,</hi> write a ſharpe Letter to the <hi>Pope,</hi> exhorting him to reforme ſome Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous Enormities, which flew from <hi>Rome</hi> as a poyſonous Fountain, and infected the whole Church? And this, and a great deal more does tell you, ſome in thoſe times there were to ſhew you, you were in danger.</p>
            <p>Whether it hath any ſhew of probability,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>14</label> that the ſaid pretended Errors, though they raſe not the Foundation of Chriſtian Faith, (as the late <hi>Proteſtants</hi> confeſs, Biſhop of <hi>Cant. p.</hi> 283.) yet they may in time endanger the raſing and deſtruction of it, as they argue, ſeeing that after the univerſall belief of them for 1000. yeares together, the Foundation yet remains undeſtroyed and entire? For if 1000. years continuance of them hath ſtood with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity of the Foundation, what appearance is there, that they will ever cauſe or induce the deſtruction of it?</p>
            <p>No, indeed, there is not a ſhew of probability,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>14</label> but there is a ſound probability of it; and this the Archbiſhop, <hi>p.</hi> 285. tells you, ſuch ill luck you have in quoting him, ſaying, that the Errors of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church are ſo many, and ſome ſo great (for which he cites Bellarmine; <hi>In prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fat. operibus praefixa</hi>) as weaken the Foundation, that it is very hard to go that way to Heaven, eſpecially to them that have had the Truth manifeſted to them.</p>
            <p>And ſurely, the Foundation once weakned is in ſome probability of being raſed and deſtroyed, even by the vertue of <hi>Gutta cavat Lapidem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Further concerning this <hi>Proteſtant</hi> diſtinction of Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors in Faith, Fundamentall and not Fundamentall,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>15</label> I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand firſt, what they underſtand by fundamentall Errors, for if they mean any nicety in ſpeculation, or Theologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call diſcourſe, it belongs not to the knowledge of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned, either therefore by a fundamentall Error, ſuch an Error in Faith as deſtroys Salvation, howſoever that
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:106321:12"/>comes to paſs, or they ſay nothing to the preſent purpoſe: This therefore ſuppoſed to be their meaning; I demand ſecondly a Catalogue and preciſe number of the funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall Errors in Faith, that is, how many and which are thoſe Errors in Faith which deſtroy Salvation? For what helps it a Chriſtian to know that there are ſuch deſtructive and damnable Errors, unleſs he knew whether he held any ſuch Errors himſelf or no? And how can he ever be certain of that, ſo long as he is ignorant, which are funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall Errors, which not? If this Catalogue be refuſed, I demand at leaſt ſome evident means or mark, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh Errors in Faith, deſtructive to Salvation or dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, from others conſiſtent with Salvation or veniall, which is neither to deny any of the Articles contained in the three Creeds, (as ſome <hi>Proteſtants</hi> have thought) for one of them puts the <hi>Proceſſion</hi> of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> from the <hi>Father</hi> and the <hi>Son,</hi> the denyall of which they neither do, nor can hold to be a fundamentall Error, unleſs they af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm the <hi>Grecian Church</hi> to erre fundamentally, and ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny it to be a true Church of Chriſt; which were quite a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſaid <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> ſeeing they maintain the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: Nor is the Creed of the Apoſtles alone a ſufficient Rule to determine fully, which are fundamentall, which not; both becauſe there are ſome things in it, which (by reaſon of the lightneſs of the matter they containe) come not by far ſo near the radicall and primary myſteries of Chriſtian Faith, as do many points controverted betwixt <hi>Proteſtants</hi> and thoſe of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cannot with any ſhew of Truth be termed funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall by <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> ſuch as are the circumſtances of Time and Perſons, as that our Saviour ſuffered under <hi>Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Pilate,</hi> and no other judge, <hi>that he roſe the third,</hi> and no other day, &amp;c. and becauſe ſome points neceſſary to the ſubſiſtance of Chriſtian Faith according to <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants,</hi> are not expreſly defined in that Creed, as, that the Holy Scriptures are the Divine word of God, which is the preciſe number of the Books of Canonicall Scriprure; whether there is any written word of God or no; or any
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:106321:12"/>Sacraments, &amp;c. So that a Chriſtian finds not all funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall points of Faith, ſet down expreſly in the Apoſtles Creed; neither is the Scripture a ſufficient Rule to know which are, which are not fundamentall points, for there are a thouſand, nay a million of Truths expreſſed in Scriptures, which touch not immediately the Foundation of Faith, as <hi>Proteſtants</hi> terme it, and no ſmall number of points accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to them fundamentall, which are not expreſt in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; as the number of Canonicall Books, the entire in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrupt purity of the Originall in any Copy or Copies, which is come to the hands of <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> &amp;c. which in their principles are ſuch points of Faith, that true Faith and conſequently Salvation cannot be obtained without them: For if ſole Scripture (as they affirm) be the Rule of Faith, and all that is in Scripture is to be believed, and nothing to be believed but what is in Scripture, or evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently deduced from it; ſeeing Faith is neceſſary to Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the determinate belief of all that is true Scripture, from which onely (they ſay) the true points of Faith are drawn, muſt be neceſſary to Salvation, and ſo a fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall point of Faith.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, I demand how any Chriſtian can affirm, that the danger of any point of Faith whatſoever, being ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently propounded as ſuch, is conſiſtent with Salvation, ſeeing all ſuch denialls or disbeliefs, include this dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable malice of attributing falſity to that which is revealed by God himſelf, as all points of Faith are, how ſmall ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the matter be which is revealed in them, which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares evidently by this example.</p>
            <p>I ſuppoſe that this ſentence of Scripture, <hi>tertia die re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurget,</hi> he ſhall riſe again the third day, is ſufficiently propounded to any one, as a point and Article of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Faith, as well according to the ſubſtance, <hi>reſurget,</hi> that our Saviour ſhould riſe again, (which <hi>Proteſtants</hi> grant to be a fundamentall point) as the circumſtance of time <hi>tertia die,</hi> the third day. Now ſuppoſe that ſome Chriſtian to whom this whole ſentence of Scripture is ſufficiently propounded, ſhould firmly believe the ſubſtance of the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:106321:13"/>Reſurrection, becauſe he eſteems it to be a fundamentall point, but ſhould disbelieve the preciſe circumſtance of time, that it was onely upon the third, and no other day; I demand ſeeing both the one and the other is propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded equally, as expreſly contained in that ſentence of Holy Scripture, whether he that disbelieves that the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection happened upon the third day and dies in that belief, can be ſaved?</p>
            <p>To your diſtinction of fundamentall and not fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>15</label> it is as much yours as ours; and what the late Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend and Learned Archbiſhop of <hi>Cant.</hi> anſwered the <hi>Jeſuit,</hi> or <hi>A. L.</hi> in that point, the ſame I give you, and beſeech you, as you will anſwer it to Almighty God, ſay, whether you do not believe the <hi>Jeſuit</hi> or <hi>A. C.</hi> was not fully ſatisfied by the Biſhop? If you will have more, thus, Points fundamentall, without believing which, an igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant man cannot be ſaved are ſet down in the Creed; points fundamentall which a learned man oppoſing, that is Maliciouſly, Schiſmatically, Heretically oppoſing are many more, even as many as the Scriptures propoſe, or the Church, the Catholick Church, either Repreſentative in a lawfull Generall Council, or otherwiſe collected alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, ſhall determine from the Scripture either Divine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or deductively.</p>
            <p>For your Catalogue, and preciſe number of fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Errors in Faith, as it came from a cunning brain, ſo I leave it where I found it.</p>
            <p>To your more modeſt demand, which are deſtructive of, and which are conſiſtent with Salvation? I anſwer, impug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning any Article of Faith, ſtubbornly and maliciouſly, is deſtructive of Salvation, disbelieving what a Church-ſhall determine, though it conſiſts not with, yet is not deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive of Salvation.</p>
            <p>To your <hi>Grecian</hi> Church erring fundamentally about the Proceſſion of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> I ſay no more then what ſome of your own have ſaid, though they diſagree in words, yet they agree in ſence, and ſo erre not funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally, thereby to make it no true Church of Chriſt,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:106321:13"/>but onely circumſtantially, and ſo remain a true Church of Chriſt; which if you do not remember, you may take it in this Diſtick.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Ex Patre &amp; Gnato procedit Spiritus Almus</l>
               <l>Quamvis diſſideat nomine Graecafides.</l>
            </q>
            <p>An Erroneous Church they may be in this particular, yet a true Church they are, notwithſtanding this particular, becauſe they deny not the Conſubſtantiality of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. For your lightneſs of matter, which the Creed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, as it came in by a Parentheſis, ſo I wiſh you had left it out, for fear ſome whether yours, or ours, I fear both, think lightly in time of all.</p>
            <p>The circumſtances of <hi>Time</hi> and <hi>Perſons, Pontius Pilate,</hi> and the <hi>Third day,</hi> are to be believed as well as the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, <hi>Chriſt ſuffering and his Reſurrection,</hi> that is, the circumſtances being maliciouſly impugned, not ſimply diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believed, will not conſiſt with Salvation.</p>
            <p>To your preciſe number of <hi>Canonicall Books of Scripture,</hi> though the Creed define them not, yet that doth not ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue the Creed not to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in them, or they in the Creed; put both together, and you have a ſufficient Rule to know which are, and which are not fundamentall points.</p>
            <p>Though the Scriptures do not tell you which are, and which are not Canonicall, yet the Church hath, and for all that the Scripture is the Rule of Faith, not the Church, becauſe the Church is but the Door and Threſhold, the Scripture, the houſe and Foundation.</p>
            <p>The incorrupt purity of the Originall, we enjoy in our Tranſlations, becauſe our Tranſlations agree with the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall; nor yet doth it follow, that the determinate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of what is true Scripture is neceſſary to Salvation; that is to all men; to all men fundamentall points are neceſſary, to ſome onely all is neceſſary.</p>
            <p>Nor is your Example ſo evident as you would have it appear; for you begin it with a <hi>ſuppoſitum, non ſupponen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum,</hi> make it your own, not another mans caſe, and <hi>deny
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:106321:14"/>the Reſurrection of Chriſt upon the Third day,</hi> or aſſign it to another if you dare, I dare not; nor dare I ſay you may be ſaved or ſhall be damned; if you do, ſuch ſecrets belong not to me, and I wiſh you not to be too buſie with them, leſt you ſcorch your fingers.</p>
            <p>I demand farther,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>16</label> That ſeeing St. <hi>Paul Heb.</hi> 11.1. ſaies, that Faith is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the ſubſtance or ground (as the Proteſtants Engliſh Bible of <hi>Anno</hi> 1648. hath it) of things hoped for, and is reckoned up by the ſame <hi>Apoſtle Heb.</hi> 6.1, 2. amongſt thoſe which are called by him <hi>Baſis,</hi> the Foundation, <hi>one of them being Faith to God,</hi> and the <hi>Apoſtle Eph.</hi> 2.20. ſaies, we are built <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, upon the foundation of the Prophets and the Apoſtles, which now according to the Proteſtants, can be nothing elſe ſave the Writings of the Prophets and Apoſtles in Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, I demand whether to ſay, that <hi>ſome points of Faith are not fundamental,</hi> or belonging to the foundation, be not as contrary to common ſenſe, as to ſay, that ſome ſtone in the foundation of a building belongs not to the foundation, or is not fundamental.</p>
            <p>Sir,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>16</label> whether the Tranſlation be <hi>Ground</hi> or <hi>Subſtance</hi> needs not trouble you, nor ſhall it me; ſince the Original will bear either, and Faith to God is one of them which are called Baſis or foundation. <hi>And we are built upon the foundation of</hi> the Prophets and <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> may ſignifie the writings of the Prophets and Apoſtles in holy Scriptures: This, and all this will not bring in your demand, whether to ſay, that ſome points of Faith are not fundamental, or belonging to the foundation, be not as contrary to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſenſe, as to ſay, that ſome ſtone in the foundation of a building belongs not to the foundation, or is not funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental? Or if it did, what harm hence to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which ſaies not, any points of Faith are not fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental?</p>
            <p>Further I demand,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>17</label> That ſeeing St. <hi>Paul</hi> affirms in the forecited place <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.2. that Laying on of hands, amongſt many other points, is the foundation, how Proteſtants can deny, that (ſeeing the Laying on of hands is disbelieved
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:106321:14"/>and rejected by them in the <hi>Sacrament of Confirmation,</hi> and by ſome in the Adminiſtration of Holy Orders, as a Popiſh Superſtition) ſuch Proteſtants differ fundamental<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from thoſe of the Roman Church? Or if the <hi>Laying on of hands</hi> belong to the foundation, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> here affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, why <hi>Annointing with Oyle,</hi> mentioned by St. <hi>James,</hi> ſhould not alſo be a fundamental point? Or why <hi>Laying on of hands</hi> (being onely, as Proteſtants eſteem it, a Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, not Sacramental) ſhould be here termed the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation and the ſubſtance of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> which all hold to be Sacramental, and more than a meer Ceremony, ſhould not be fundamental? Or laſtly, what reaſon there is to ſay, that <hi>Laying on of hands</hi> hath a neerer connexion to the radical and prime myſteries of our Faith, then ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other points controverted betwixt Proteſtants and thoſe of the Roman Church?</p>
            <p>Whether by <hi>Laying on of hands</hi> here is intended <hi>Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,</hi> which to be a Sacrament, properly ſo taken,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>17</label> will be hard for you to prove, but not hard for me to grant, <hi>that it is Sacramentale quoddam,</hi> and yet not <hi>Sacramentum</hi> for want of <hi>viſibile ſignum inviſibilis gratiae,</hi> and yet hard again for you to make it a foundation, the uſe whereof is not disbelieved or rejected by us. No, the diſuſe of it is lamented, and let them anſwer it who have cauſed it. Yes, and <hi>Laying on of hands</hi> in the Adminiſtration of Holy Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders is uſed by all thoſe who are ordained Epiſcopally; and yet no Sacrament for all that, though we confeſs it a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation <hi>quoad Eccleſiaſtices,</hi> not <hi>quoad Eccleſiam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Why <hi>Annointing with Oyle,</hi> mentioned by St. <hi>James,</hi> ſhould not be a fundamental point, you might have told your ſelf without demand from others, becauſe the Epiſtle of St. <hi>James,</hi> and ſome other Books, were not received into the Canon of the Scripture, untill ſome time after the Foundation was laid.</p>
            <p>Nor is <hi>Laying on of hands</hi> eſteemed by <hi>Proteſtants</hi> a Ceremony not Sacramentall, nor is it by St. <hi>Paul</hi> termed the Foundation, and ſubſtance of the Euchariſt.</p>
            <p>We all, you and we hold the <hi>Eucharist</hi> to be a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:106321:15"/>and not onely Sacramentall but Fundamentall, that is, <hi>Inadultis:</hi> Nor do I remember that I ever read, that <hi>Laying on of hands</hi> hath a nearer connexion to the radicall and prime Myſteries of our Faith, (unleſs onely <hi>in Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticis</hi>) then many other points controverted betwixt <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and thoſe of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church.</p>
            <p>It is yet further demanded,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>18</label> ſeeing <hi>Proteſtants</hi> affirm, that the whole Catholick viſible Church may erre in the definition of points of Faith, not fundamentall, and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that they affirm, that the points in difference betwixt us are not fundamentall, and ſo not neceſſary to Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and laſtly ſeeing they affirm alſo, that the Scriptures may be obſcure in points not neceſſary to Salvation; by what means can they ever think to convince the <hi>Roman</hi> Church of Error in theſe points of difference betwixt them and her?</p>
            <p>Sir,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>18</label> with your favour, <hi>Proteſtants</hi> do not affirm that the whole Catholick Church can erre in Doctrines abſolutely fundamentall, and neceſſary to all mens Salvation; for ſo we ſhould deſtroy an Article of our Creed. <hi>I believe the Holy Catholick Church,</hi> which conſiſts of Triumphant ſouls, as well as Militant men; but that this or that vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Church, or the whole viſible Church and Catholick, as limitted to viſible, may erre in the definition of points not fundamentall; yes, and fundamentall too <hi>Proteſtants</hi> do affirm, and the reaſon is, becauſe the whole viſible Church conſiſts of men; and men when they are at beſt, are ſubject to Error.</p>
            <p>Nor do <hi>Proteſtants</hi> affirm the points in difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt you and them, to be not fundamentall or unneceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to Salvation; for ſome of them, are ſo fundamentall, and neceſſary to Salvation to you, and ſuch learned men as you are, that unleſs you leave them, you will hardly finde the way to Heaven; take one for all, and let the <hi>Merit of your own works be it,</hi> and ſee if your ſharing with Chriſt in earning a part of your Salvation, will not loſe you the whole; and ſo by this, the reſt of this Queſtion is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, and the <hi>Roman</hi> Church convinced of Error in
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:106321:15"/>points of difference betwixt them and her.</p>
            <p>Seeing alſo, that every point of Faith is a Divine Truth,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>19</label> proceeding from the Revelation of God, and to be belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved (as I ſuppoſe for the preſent with the common con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of <hi>Proteſtants</hi>) with an infallible aſſent of Faith, if the univerſall viſible Church may erre, and the Scripture may be obſcure, as is generally affirmed by our Adverſaries in points of Faith not fundamentall, how ſhall ſuch points as are in Controverſie betwixt us and are accounted by <hi>Proteſtants</hi> not fundamentall, or not neceſſary to Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, be diſcerned to be points of Faith, or how agreed this Modern <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Doctrine of no difference betwixt us, in points neceſſary to Salvation, which that of their beginners, and more antient Predeceſſors, who taught that the Scriptures were clear onely in all points neceſſary to Salvation, and upon that pretext both affirmed that our Doctrines againſt them, were clearly convinced of falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood by the Authority of ſole Scripture, and allowed all Lay-people promiſcuouſly to read them, as being clear to them in all the points controverted betwixt us, for this manifeſtly ſuppoſes, that they were held by thoſe begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, to be points of Faith neceſſary to Salvation, or fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentals: Or what means is there to believe them as points of Faith, ſeeing they can never be believed infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly upon the Churches Authority, by reaſon of her pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended fallibility in them, nor expreſly for the Authority of Scripture, by reaſon of its obſcurity in the delivery of them, according to the principles of <hi>Proteſtants?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That every point of Faith as divine Truth,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>19</label> proceeding from the Revelation of God, (if you are not equivocall in that expreſſion) is to be believed, is granted, but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (as you ſuppoſe with a common conſent of <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi>) with an infallible aſſent of Faith, I cannot ſay; for if by infallible aſſent you mean a full aſſurance, or great confidence, I can tell you <hi>Proteſtants</hi> are not ſo bold, we confeſs aſſurance to be the effect of a ſtrong Faith, we affirm it not to be the Eſſence of all Faith.</p>
            <p>If the univerſall viſible Church may erre, and the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:106321:16"/>Scriptures may be obſcure as is generally affirmed by out Adverſaries in points of Faith not fundamentall, how ſhall ſuch points as are in Controverſie betwixt us, and are accounted by <hi>Proteſtants</hi> not fundamentall, or not neceſſary to Salvation, be diſcerned to be points of Faith? How the univerſall viſible Church may erre, I told you in the former; and how the Scriptures may be obſcure, and to whom, I tell you in this; <hi>Proteſtants</hi> do not generally affirm them obſcure in points not fundamentall, though if they did, it were nothing to the purpoſe in points con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted betwixt us.</p>
            <p>That Scriptures are the Rule of Faith, which is funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental, is by Proteſtants affirmed.</p>
            <p>That the Scriptures are eaſie and plain to all ſorts of men, learned and unlearned, which uſe the means, and are diligent in reading them, is likewiſe affirmed; when they are obſcure to any, they are obſcure to them onely who have not eyes enlightned to ſee into them; they who have humble and diligent ſouls will ſoon diſcern, which be, and which be not, points of Faith.</p>
            <p>How our predeceſſor; and modern Proteſtants agree, need no further demonſtration then what is already given; that the Scriptures are cleer onely in all points neceſſary to Salvation, is for you to prove.</p>
            <p>Pretext we know none, your Doctrines againſt us are clearly convinced by Authority of Scripture, not alone but of expoſitors alſo.</p>
            <p>Lay-people allowed by <hi>Proteſtants</hi> to read the Scriptures, and ſo they were by the Primitive Fathers; and ſo they would by you, if you would follow Primitive and Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick example; we hold them clear in points of Faith ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to Salvation; which though not believed infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly upon the Churches Authority, by reaſon of her (not pretended) fallibility, yet are believed expreſly for and by the Authority of Scripture; without any obſcurity in the delivery of them, not according to the principall of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants</hi> onely, but of the Primitive Fathers alſo.</p>
            <p>I demand further,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>20</label> if the whole viſible Church may erre
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:106321:16"/>in the definition of any points whatſoever, that Error muſt either proceed from ignorance and want of light, or from malice and want of vertue and goodneſs; not the ſecond, for then the whole viſible Church of <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhould not be <hi>ſancta,</hi> Holy, as it is believed to be in our Creed, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in the Scriptures, but ſhould become a Harlot, and abominable deceiver of the world, and a ſeducer of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, in teaching contrary to the known truth: not the firſt, for if ſhe could erre out of ignorance, to what pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe do Proteſtants appear to her Determination in a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and general Council, in any of the points of difference betwixt them and thoſe of the Roman Church, ſeeing ſhe may through ignorance erre in the determination of them, as being not fundamental according to them, neither can it be ſaid, notwithſtanding the whole viſible Churches fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libility in points not fundamental, nay, though it ſhould actually erre, and that Error ſhould be evidently diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, yet even thoſe, who had thus evidently diſcovered the ſaid Errors, were to conforme themſelves to thoſe errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous definitions of a general Council; for if this confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity be underſtood of an internal conformity in Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as it is wholly impoſſible, ſeeing that were to judge the ſame thing to be true and not true at the ſame time, and to judge againſt an evident knowledge: and if it be underſtood of an external conformity and profeſſion onely, it were manifeſtly impious and high <hi>Hypocriſie</hi> in reſiſting the known Truth, revealed by Almighty God, which they evidently know to be a moſt falſe Error in Faith.</p>
            <p>Secondly, if one were to ſubſcribe and externally to conform himſelf to the definitions of lawful general Councils, which one perſwades himſelf he evidently knows to be erroneous, till another be aſſembled to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect them; why did not Proteſtants afford this external conformity to the definition of the general Councils of <hi>Florence,</hi> of <hi>Lateran,</hi> and to the ſecond Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> (to omit others) till ſome other lawful general Council came to correct their pretended Errors, they having no
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:106321:17"/>other reaſon to reject the authority of the ſaid Councils, then that they define many things againſt the Proteſtant Doctrine?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, ſeeing it was never yet ſeen, nor can be ever made manifeſt, that any lawful general Council revoked any definition in matter of Faith of any former lawful ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Council, what hope is there, that they ſhould now begin to do what was never done before them?</p>
            <p>Fourthly, if it were ſuppoſed that any ſuch revocatory definition ſhould iſſue from them, that party, whoſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine ſhould be condemned by ſuch revocations, would accuſe the Council of Error, as much as the contrary party accuſed the former Council of error in defining againſt them, and ſo the controverſie would remain as indetermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as it was before; neither would it be poſſible to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine it fully by a general Council, for the party con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned would ſtill expect another Council to revoke that definition, which ſeems to him evidently erroneous, and ſo there would be no end of new determinations and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations <hi>in infinitum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet farther, ſeeing lawfull Generall Councils do not onely oblige, even under pain of Anathema, or being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed and excommunicated, all Chriſtians to believe and profeſs the Doctrine which they teach them, not onely to be true and free from Error, but to be divine Truth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed by God himſelf, if they ſhould erre in any ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition, they muſt make God the Father of Error and untruth, which quite deſtroys the veracity of God, and conſequently overthrowes the main and primary founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſtian Faith, and therefore muſt neceſſarily be held to include a fundamentall Error: So impoſſible and implicatory a thing it is, for them to erre in matter of Faith, and not to erre fundamentally. For either that erring Council muſt define ſome poſitive Error, or that which God never revealed to be revealed from God, or that ſome true Revelation from God is an Error. Both which con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ine no leſſe malice then this, <hi>To make God a Lyer.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:106321:17"/>
            <p>How the whole viſible Church may erre,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>20</label> you have heard; now whether from Ignorance or Malice you would know; from malice I think not, becauſe then it would not be <hi>Sancta,</hi> Holy, as you ſay moſt rightly; but why not from Ignorance? For they are but men, and men at beſt know not all things, they know but in part; and yet we appeale to the determination of her, in a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Generall Council, becauſe what ſhe knowes in part, and what you know in part, and what we know in part, may amount to more then half the whole; and therein we ſhall acquieſce untill we know perfectly.</p>
            <p>So then, the malicious, erroneous definition of a Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Council, if lawfully called, being declined, we ſhall ſtudy conformity, both internall in judgement, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall in profeſſion, without ſinning, either againſt evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent knowledge within, or by high Hypocriſie with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out.</p>
            <p>And yet why we conformed not to the definitions of the Generall Councils, (as you call them) of <hi>Florence,</hi> of <hi>Lateran,</hi> and the ſecond of <hi>Nice,</hi> you know, if you would expreſs it as well as we; not ſo much for defining many things againſt our, as againſt the Catholick Doctrine.</p>
            <p>Nor thirdly, is all hope taken away from doing what was never done, (as you ſay, but moſt untruly) becauſe ſome Generall Councils have revoked what former Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Councils lawfully called have determined.</p>
            <p>And fourthly, upon ſuppoſition, that any ſuch revocatory definition ſhould iſſue; that either you or our ſelves, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of our Doctrines being condemned, ſhould ſtill ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect another Council to revoke that definition? For cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly the Catholick Chriſtian will be ſo modeſt, as to ſtand to the definition of that ſpirituall power, which he acknowledgeth the higheſt upon Earth, though the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick <hi>Roman</hi> would not unleſs the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> both called and commanded the Council, and ſo the <hi>In infini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> would be yours, not ours.</p>
            <p>And farther let it be granted, that lawfull Generall Councils do oblige under pain of <hi>Anathema</hi> to believe
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:106321:18"/>and profeſs that Doctrine which they teach to be free from Error, and a divine Truth revealed by God himſelf, ſo it be not a new Revelation againſt the old; we would not believe they make God the Author of Error, or a Lyer, you may do it if you pleaſe, or dare.</p>
            <p>Seeing St.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>21</label> 
               <hi>Paul Eph.</hi> 4.14. affirmes that our Saviour had appointed Paſtors and Teachers till the day of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as a means to preſerve Chriſtian people from being carryed about <hi>with every wind of Doctrine,</hi> cannot be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood disjunctively: For then, if thoſe Paſtors preſerved them, from being ſeduced in one onely point of Chriſtian Doctrine, it would not be true, that they preſerved them from being carryed about <hi>with every wind of Doctrine;</hi> but they muſt be underſtood <hi>Conjunctively,</hi> that is, that they preſerve them from being carryed away <hi>with any wind of Doctrine</hi> whatſoever, which ſhould chance to be buzzed into their Eares by falſe Teachers; now ſeeing ſuch winds of erroneous Doctrine are raiſed as well in points which <hi>Proteſtants</hi> account not fundamentall, as in fundamentals, the meaning of the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> then muſt be, that by meanes of theſe Paſtors, Chriſtians be preſerved from following any Error in Faith, whether it be fundamentall or not fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall, and conſequently that they can aſſuredly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect them to eſchew all Errors in Faith, which they could not do, if they themſelves were ſubject to teach them any Errors, or ſeduce them by any winde of Doctrine what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever.</p>
            <p>Seeing alſo, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> in the ſame place <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.10. tells us that the ſaid Paſtors, are to Conſummate the Saints, and to build up the Myſticall body of Chriſt, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand whether the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> by theſe words make not thoſe Paſtors able to ſecure Chriſtian people from Error, not onely in the Foundation (as <hi>Protestants</hi> terme it) but in ſuperſtructures alſo, for otherwiſe they would have been inſtituted by our Saviour onely to found his Myſticall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy the Church, but not to build it up, and to ground and initiate the Saints, but not to Conſummate them?</p>
            <p>Sir,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>21</label> whether your expoſition of St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Text,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:106321:18"/>
               <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.14. be current or not, is a Queſtion; if it be, why may not the words be undeſtood <hi>disjunctively,</hi> as well as <hi>conjunctively?</hi> Your own Predeceſſors the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> thought ſo, where they ſay upon theſe words, the uſe of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Governors (not all Paſtors and Teachers) is to keep us in the Unity and conſtancy of the Catholick Faith, that we be not carryed away with the blaſt and wind of every Hereſie, (and there are Errors and windes of Doctrine beſides Hereſies,) which is a proper note of Sects, and new Doctrine which trouble the infirme weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings of this Church; as ſometimes the <hi>Arrians,</hi> then the <hi>Manichees,</hi> then the <hi>Neſtorians,</hi> then the <hi>Latherans</hi> and <hi>Calviniſts</hi> and ſuch like; ſo the <hi>Rhemiſts,</hi> they might have left the laſt out, as being yet uncondemned of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie; but you will have the words underſtood <hi>Conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively, That the people be preſerved from being carryed away with any wind of Doctrine whatſoever,</hi> and if this be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted you, what get you by it more then <hi>Turpe eſt Doctori;</hi> for I pray what Paſtors or Teachers have carryed about ſilly people, with ſuch windes and kindes of Doctrine as theſe?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That Chriſt deſcended onely in Limbum Patrum, a high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er part of Hell. That ſome ſinners go into Purgatory, a ſide part of Hell. That half a Sacrament is enough,</hi> contrary to Chriſts Inſtitution, and the Catholick Churches practiſe for 1000. years. <hi>That the intention of the Prieſt is of the eſſence of Baptiſm. That worſhip is due to Images. That there is a Tranſubſtantiation; a converſion of the Bread and Wine into the Body and Blood of Christ corporally.</hi> I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear a new Creed made at the no general or lawful Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> and many more ſuch winds of <hi>Doctrine</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with you have carried about ſome ſouls.</p>
            <p>To your other Text <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.10. and your demand upon it, whether the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> by theſe words, <hi>To conſumniate the Saints, and to build up the Myſtical body of Chriſt,</hi> make not thoſe Paſtors able to ſecure Chriſtian people from er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, not onely in the foundation, but in the ſuperſtructures alſo? Sure I think not; for the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> himſelf was ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:106321:19"/>by God, and ſo are all Paſtors that do their duty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientiouſly. The Apoſtle onely tels the ſucceeding Paſtors their duty, and wo to them if they do it not, he enables them not to do it.</p>
            <p>If it ſhould be anſwered,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>22</label> that theſe and ſuch like pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes or inſtitutions of Chriſt are onely conditional, that is, truly intended on his part, but yet may be fruſtrated by the malice of ſuch as correſpond not to his intention; and therefore though he intend that theſe Paſtors ſhould per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the ſaid Offices in the Church, yet that it involved this condition, if they were not wanting on their parts, but by their failing the inſtitution of Chriſt is made fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate and of no effect.</p>
            <p>I anſwer to this prophane and unchriſtian Objection, firſt, that if Chriſts promiſes and inſtitutions be thus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>efficacious and conditional, that notwithſtanding the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes that Chriſt hath made for the preſervation of his Church, yet by the malice of Chriſtians, or others, the whole Chriſtian Church may utterly fail and come to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. Secondly, that it may erre even in fundamental points, (contrary to the Doctrine of Proteſtants) and ſo become a Synagogue of Satan. Thirdly, that the ancient Promiſes of the coming of the Meſſias, of the REdempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Mankind, of the ſaving of ſome at the laſt Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp;c. have no abſolute certainty in them, and ſo by the malice of men might have been, or may be fruſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, that by this there is no certain credit to be given to any Promiſe or Inſtitution of God or Chriſt, in the whole Old or New Teſtament, for a thouſand diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent conditions may be invented, which not being perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med or put, the prediction failes: Thus one may ſay (upon the like grounds) that as the promiſes of benefits and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings may be hindred by the malice and demerits of wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed perſons, ſo the threats &amp; thundrings of puniſhments up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſinners may be hindred by the vertues and good works of Saints; and becauſe we have no rule to know what pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of goodneſs or malice is ſufficient to fruſtrate ſuch
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:106321:19"/>predictions, we remain wholly uncertain, whether they ſhall be abſolutely verified or no, unleſs therefore this principle be ſetled, that all divine Inſtitutions and Predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions are to be held abſolute, and never to be fruſtrated, whenſoever it is not evidently apparent, that they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional, and may be hindred, there can be no certainty that any Inſtitution or prediction in the whole Scripture ſhall be abſolutely fulfilled.</p>
            <p>Seeing therefore it is not evident that this inſtitution, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and others of the ſame nature concerning the Church are conditionall, they are to be ſuppoſed to be abſolute, and not to be fruſtrated by any malice of men whatſoever.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, no <hi>Proteſtants</hi> who hold the whole viſible Church cannot periſh, nor all the Paſtors prove wilfull Seducers, can apply this anſwer to the Text now cited, <hi>viz. Eph.</hi> 4. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for if it be hindered by the malice of the ſaid Paſtors, they muſt with joynt conſent maliciouſly teach falſe Doctrine, to be the Doctrine of Chriſt, which were to teach fundamentall Errors, and to fall off from Chriſt. If this ſolution may paſs for current, who can be certainly aſſured, that there is any true Church of Chriſt, viſible or inviſible exiſtent now in the world? for all the promiſes concerning the continuance of it to the worlds end, may be as well ſaid to be as well conditionall and fruſtrate by the malice of men, as this, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and who knowes that the ſaid malice is not already grown to that height, that it hath deſerved, that God ſhould take his true Church quite out of the world, and ſo that there is now no true Church exiſtent in all the world?</p>
            <p>Sir, in this long paſſage,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>22</label> you have fought onely with your own wind; inſtead of a Queſtion, you have ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed an Anſwer, and then given your own Anſwer to your own Queſtioning Anſwer, or Anſwering Queſtion, both which being full enough of—I leave it as I find it, unleſs you will have a Syllogiſme without a Syllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſme, Anſwer a Queſtion without a Queſtion, and then you ſhall have it thus.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:106321:20"/>
            <p>That which was never Queſtioned or Anſwered, ought not now to be Queſtioned or Anſwered; but the fruſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Gods predictions (conditionall or abſolute,) by mans malice or merits was never Queſtioned or Anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, therefore now ought not to be Queſtioned or Anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
            <p>Such as theſe may well come out of a Jeſuiticall Court, but never yet came from the Catholick Church: Sir, I muſt and do tell you, there is little leſs then Blaſphemy in your ſuppoſition, and ſomewhat more then little leſs in your poſition; this is beyond, <hi>Nihil dictum quod non dictum fuit prius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whether it be not evident,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>23</label> that unlearned <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> who cannot determine differences in Religion, either by force of Argument or places of Scripture, but muſt wholly depend in the choice of their Faith, upon Authority and Credit of Chriſtian Teachers, are not obliged in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to prefer that Authority and credibility of Doctors, which all circumſtances conſidered is abſolutely and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionably the greater Authority?</p>
            <p>No,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>23</label> it is not yet evident; for unlearned <hi>Proteſtants</hi> can determine differences in Religion, if not by force of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, yet by places of Scripture; which they of <hi>Rome</hi> cannot do; and the reaſon is ready, they deny their Laity, we allow ours to read the Scripture, and therefore need not depend upon their Teachers, but upon the Teacher of us all; nor have you yet proved your Authority, unque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionably the greater, but unqueſtionably the leaſt of all Authorities, unleſs you take it, <hi>Senſu Romano non Catholico,</hi> what the next produces we ſhall ſee.</p>
            <p>Whether that Authority of Doctors,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>24</label> where thoſe of one ſide are equall at leaſt, if not exceeding them of the contrary party in Learning, Wiſdome, Zeal, Sanctity, Vertue, Sincerity and all other Qualities and Perfections, which confer to the accompliſhment of complete Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, in Chriſtian Teacher, and with this equality incomparably exceed the Doctors of the other party, in number, is not in all prudence to be judged
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:106321:20"/>abſolutely, and unqueſtionably the greateſt Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty?</p>
            <p>To paſs your impertinences of <hi>Idem</hi> upon <hi>Idem,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>24</label> and your over-weening opinion of exceeding the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> party in Learning, Wiſdome, Zeal, Sincerity, Virtue, Sanctity; to which adde but the Scripture, and we will acknowledge a complete Authority, and ſubmit to the expoſition of that Authority in the ſenſe of the <hi>four firſt Generall Councils,</hi> and the Fathers of the firſt 800. years, or a preſent lawfully called Generall Council; to which if you will do the like, we ſhall then praiſe God, for the fruition of what we yet pray for, the Peace and Unity of Chriſtendom.</p>
            <p>Whether this equality at leaſt in all the ſaid perfections,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>25</label> is not to be found in the <hi>Roman</hi> Doctors compared with thoſe of the <hi>Proteſtants?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let the equality at leaſt,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>25</label> be granted in all the ſaid per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, <hi>Quoad hominem,</hi> though the Compariſon ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers not well, what you gaine by it, we may ſee anon.</p>
            <p>Whether this forementioned equalizing the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Doctors, thoſe of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>26</label> the many yeares of their continuance, and univerſall extent of their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, conſidered, exceed not incomparably in number thoſe of the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> profeſſion?</p>
            <p>No; it doth not,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>26</label> neither incomparably nor yet compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably, for the many years of continuance will exceed on our part, ſo that you divide the years equally from 800. to 800. and then judge your ſelves, which 800. <hi>years</hi> comes neareſt to the primitive purity in matter of Religion, your 800. or our 800. Name but one general Council, or any number of Fathers for the firſt 800. exceeding our number, <hi>&amp; actum eſt,</hi> the field is yours.</p>
            <p>Whether this equality in perfections,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>27</label> and incomparable exceſs in number conſidered, all unlearned <hi>Proteſtants</hi> are not obliged, both in Prudence and Conſcience to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the Authority of the <hi>Roman</hi> Doctors, before that of <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and conſequently to follow the <hi>Roman</hi> and deſert the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Doctrine?</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:106321:21"/>
            <p>No,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>27</label> not yet, for all this is but <hi>Id<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m per idem</hi> ſtill, onely you have now added Conſcience to Prudence, adde but Scripture to your Roman Doctors, and that Scripture expounded by the firſt 800. <hi>years,</hi> either <hi>repreſentatively</hi> or <hi>ſucceſſively,</hi> or by a preſent lawfully called <hi>general Council,</hi> and we ſhall have conſcience, yours and ours, ruled by prudence, and prudence following conſcience, and by both Unity reſtored.</p>
            <p>Whether upon the foreſaid conſiderations the Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Doctors,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>28</label> in all things wherein they contradict the <hi>Romans,</hi> is not contemptible, and unable to ſway the judgement of any prudent Chriſtian, to frame any moral eſteem of it; for though in matters wherein they are ſeconded, or not contradicted by an Authority incomparably greater than their own, they may deſervedly be eſteemed for their Naturall Abilities, and Morall Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities worthy of Credit, yet in all things wherein they ſtand in oppoſition and contradiction againſt an Authority incomparably exceeding theirs, they deſerve nothing but to be ſleighted and contemned, by all thoſe who are to be led by the ſole force of Authority: Thus when <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant</hi> Doctors affirm, that either the Scriptures or Fathers are for them, and againſt the <hi>Roman</hi> Church; what they ſay in this is not to be regarded, ſeeing the Authority of the <hi>Roman</hi> Doctors, abſolutely greater then theirs, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>animouſly affirm the quite contrary; thus when they affirm, that the <hi>Roman</hi> Church is full of Errors and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions, crept in they know neither <hi>when,</hi> nor <hi>how,</hi> their accuſation is to be ſleighted, being clearly and conſtantly contradicted by a far greater Authority.</p>
            <p>Thus when they ſay, that <hi>Proteſtants</hi> may be ſaved, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and dying wilfully in their Religion, they deſerve no Credit at all, for the quite contrary is moſt conſtantly defended by the incomparably ſtronger Authority of the <hi>Roman</hi> Doctors, &amp; the like is to be affirmed in all points of difference betwixt the two Religions; ſo that a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> is not to conſider the Abilities and Authority of his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, abſolutely or in matters out of Controverſie, but as
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:106321:21"/>contradicting an Authority incomparably excelling theirs, in which contradiction they deſerve neither Credit nor Eſteem.</p>
            <p>It was once, twice trice before but an equalizing,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>28</label> but it is now once, twice, thrice, four times an incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably greater Authority, and all this is, <hi>Gratis dictum:</hi> prove your Authority greater, and but greater without in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparably then ours, and we yield; in the mean time, you ſhall give me leave to ſend you this Syllogiſme for an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to your Queſtion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Proteſtants</hi> alleadging Scripture expounded by the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers for the firſt 800. yeares, are at leaſt of an equall Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority with the Church, and Doctors of <hi>Rome,</hi> alleadging Scripture without the expoſition of thoſe Fathers; but <hi>Proteſtants</hi> ſo alleadge Scripture, and ſo the <hi>Roman</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors alleadge Scripture.</p>
            <p>Therefore the <hi>Protestants</hi> are of an equal Authority at leaſt with the <hi>Roman</hi> Doctors. You will be forced to confeſſe more than my modeſty challenges, in the mean time I ſuſpect you for an incomparably cholerick proud man, contending more for <hi>Triumph</hi> than <hi>Truth,</hi> and till you have incomparably proved your Authority, ſeek not to Proſelitize an unlearned <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> to captivate his Faith and Religion to <hi>Roman</hi> Doctors without Faith or Religion.</p>
            <p>I demand farther,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>29</label> That if the Authority of all the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of the whole Body of <hi>Protestants</hi> be ſo inconſiderable in compariſon with thoſe of the <hi>Roman</hi> Doctors, how much leſs will be the Authority of any one Sect or Party of them, and then how minute and ſcarce perceptible will be the Authority of a <hi>Laud,</hi> a <hi>Hammond,</hi> a <hi>Chilling-worth,</hi> a <hi>Ferne,</hi> a <hi>Bramhall,</hi> a <hi>Taylor,</hi> &amp;c. who now obtain ſo powerful an aſcendant upon the hearts of our modern <hi>Lay proteſtants,</hi> ſeeing they are in a manner nothing in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the Authority of the <hi>Roman</hi> Doctors?</p>
            <p>Authoritatively ſupoken of your <hi>Roman</hi> Doctors,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>29</label> and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutely ſpoken of <hi>Proteſtants;</hi> but, I pray, whom do you intend by <hi>Laud?</hi> ſo you ſtile him, I knew him Mr. <hi>William
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:106321:22"/>Land,</hi> Dr. <hi>William Laud,</hi> Lord Biſhop <hi>William Laud,</hi> Lord Archbiſhop <hi>William Laud,</hi> and know not you his Conference with <hi>Fiſher,</hi> Mr. <hi>Fiſher,</hi> or Dr. <hi>Fiſher,</hi> if he at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained ſo high, be anſwered Sir.</p>
            <p>I can tell you of a Gentleman yet living, who in <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople,</hi> at one bout, heard ten of your Doctors rejoyce much at the Archbiſhops death, becauſe he was the great, if not the greateſt enemy your <hi>Roman</hi> Church ever had, and this becauſe he laboured for an Unity and Reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſtendom: anſwer him when you pleaſe or can, and till then let him enjoy peace in his Grave, without your detracting him, as not living to give you his own an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Chillingworth,</hi> ſo you, Mr. <hi>Chillingworth,</hi> ſo I, is dead too, I pray you when will you anſwer <hi>his Letter</hi> to Mr. <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiger</hi> a brother of your own, and which I have now ſent you, till you do, let him be in peace too.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Good Maſter</hi> Lewiger,</head>
                  <p>THough I am reſolved not to be much afflicted for the loſs of that which is not in my power to keep, yet I cannot deny but the loſs of a friend goes very near to my heart; and by this name of friend I did preſume, till of late, I might have called you; becauſe that perhaps for want of power and opportunity, I have done you no good office; yet I have been alwaies willing and ready to do you the beſt ſervice I could: And therefore I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but admire at the affected ſtrangeneſſe, which in your laſt letter to me, you ſeemed to take upon you; renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing in a manner all relation to me, and tacitly excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicating me from all intereſt in you: The ſuperſcription of your letter to me is, to Mr. <hi>W. C.</hi> and your ſubſcription is, <hi>John L.</hi> as if you either diſdained, or made conſcience of ſtyling me your friend, or your ſelf mine: If this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from reaſon, I pray ſhew it; If it proceed from paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or weakneſs, I pray mend it: If you think me one of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:106321:22"/>thoſe, to whom St. <hi>John</hi> forbids you to ſay, God ſave you, then you are to think &amp; prove me one of thoſe deceivers, which denyed Jeſus Chriſt to be come in the fleſh: If you think me an Heretick, and therefore to be avoided, you muſt prove me <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, by my own judgement, which I know I cannot, and therefore you cannot: If you ſay, I do not hear the Church, and therefore am to be eſteemed an Heathen or Publican, you are to prove then, that by the Church is meant the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> And yet when you have done ſo, I hope Chriſtians are not forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to ſhew Humanity and Civility even to Pagans: For Gods ſake Mr. <hi>L.</hi> free your ſelf from this blind zeal at leaſt for a little ſpace; and conſider with reaſon and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, what ſtrange crime you can charge me with, that I ſhould deſerve this ſtrange uſage, eſpecially from you.</p>
                  <p>Is it a crime with all my underſtanding to endeavour to find your Religion true, and to make my ſelf a believer of it, and not to be able to do ſo? Is it a crime to employ all my reaſon upon the juſtification of the infallibility of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, and to find it impoſſible to be juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied? I will call God to witneſs, who knowes my heart better then you do, that I have evened the ſcale of my judgement as much as poſſibly I could, and have not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly allowed any one graine of worldly motives on either ſide, but have weighed the reaſons for your Religion, and againſt it, with ſuch indifferencie, as if there were nothing in the world but God and my ſelf: and is it my fault that the ſcale goes down, which hath the moſt weight in it? that the building falls which hath a falſe Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Have you ſuch power over your underſtanding, that you can believe what you pleaſe, though you ſee no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon? or that you can ſuſpend your belief when you do ſee reaſon? If you have, I pray for our old friendſhip ſake, teach me that trick; and until I have learnt it, I pray blame me not for going the ordinary way; I mean, for believing, or not believing, as I ſee reaſon: If you can convince me of wilfull oppoſition againſt the known truth, of negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:106321:23"/>in ſeeking it, of unwillingneſs to find it, of prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring temporall reſpect before it, or of any other fault that is in my power to amend: It is indeed a fault, if I amend it not, be as angry with me as you pleaſe: But to impute unto me unvoluntary Errors, or that I do not ſee what I would ſee, but cannot, or that I will not profeſs what I do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, certainly this is a far more reaſonable Error, then any you can juſtly charge me withall; for let me tell you, that imputing <hi>Socinianiſme</hi> to me, (whoſoever was the Author of it) was a wicked and groundleſs ſlander: Perhaps you will ſay (for this is the uſuall ſong of your ſide) that Pride is a voluntary fault, and with this I am juſtly chargeable, for forſaking the <hi>Guide,</hi> which God hath appointed me to follow; but what if I forſook it, becauſe I thought I had reaſon to fear it was one of thoſe blind <hi>Guides,</hi> which whoſoever blindly followes, is threatned by our <hi>Saviour</hi> that both he and his <hi>Guide</hi> ſhall fall into the <hi>Duch?</hi> Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> I hope you will grant, it was not <hi>Pride</hi> but <hi>Conſcience</hi> that moved me ſo to do; for as it is a wiſe humiliation to obey thoſe, whom God hath ſet over me; ſo it is a ſinfull Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulity, to follow every man or every <hi>Church,</hi> that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out warrant will take upon them to be my <hi>Guides:</hi> Shew then ſome good and evident title which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath to this office; produce but one reaſon for it, which upon triall will not finally be reſolved and vaniſh into uncertainties, and if I yield not unto it, ſay, (if you pleaſe) I am as proud as <hi>Lucifer:</hi> In the meane time, give me leave to think it ſtrange, and not far from a Prodigie, that the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the <hi>Roman Church,</hi> being the <hi>Guide</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> if it be true <hi>Doctrine,</hi> ſhould either not be known to the four <hi>Evangeliſts,</hi> or if it were known to them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wiſe and good men, they ſhould either be ſo envious of the <hi>Churches</hi> happineſs, or ſo forgetfull of the work they took in hand (which was to write the whole <hi>Goſpell</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi>) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s not ſo much as one of them ſhould mention ſo much as once this ſo neceſſary a part of the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the belief whereof there is no <hi>Salvation,</hi> and with the belief whereof (unleſs men be ſnatcht away by ſuddain death) there is hardly any <hi>Damnation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:106321:23"/>
                  <p>It is evident they do all of them with one conſent ſpeak very plainly of many things of no importance in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon hereof; and is it credible, or indeed poſſible, that with one Torrent, or rather conſpiracy, they ſhould be ſo deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſilent concerning this <hi>Unum neceſſarium?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>You may believe it if you can, for my part I cannot, unleſs I ſee demonſtration for it: For if you ſay, they ſend us to the <hi>Church,</hi> and conſequently to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> this is to ſuppoſe that which can never be proved, <hi>viz.</hi> That the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> is the onely <hi>Church,</hi> and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this ſuppoſition upon the diviſion of the <hi>Church,</hi> I am as far to ſeek for a <hi>guide</hi> of my <hi>faith</hi> as ever; as for Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, In that great diviſion of the Church, when the whole world wondred (ſaith St. <hi>Hierome</hi>) that it was become <hi>Arrian,</hi> when <hi>Liberius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> (as St. <hi>Athana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius,</hi> St. <hi>Hierome,</hi> and St. <hi>Hillary</hi> teſtifie) ſubſcribed their <hi>Hereſie,</hi> and joyned in Communion with them: or in the diviſion of the <hi>Greek</hi> and the <hi>Roman Church</hi> about the <hi>Proceſſion</hi> of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> when either ſide was the <hi>Church</hi> unto it ſelf, and each part <hi>heretical</hi> or <hi>ſchiſmatical</hi> to the other; what direction could I then (an ignorant man) have found from that <hi>Text</hi> of <hi>Scripture, Unleſs he hear the Church let him be unto thee as an Heathen or a Publicane:</hi> or <hi>upon this rock I will build my Church, and the gates of hell ſhall not prevail againſt it?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Again, give me leave to wonder, that neither St. <hi>Paul,</hi> writing to the <hi>Romans,</hi> ſhould ſo much as intimate this their <hi>priviledge</hi> of <hi>Infallibility;</hi> but rather the contrary, <hi>put them in fear,</hi> in the 11. <hi>Chapter, becauſe they as well as the Jews were in danger of falling away.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That St. <hi>Peter,</hi> your pretended <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting two <hi>Catholick Epiſtles,</hi> mentioning his departure, ſhould not once acquaint the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> whom he writes to, what <hi>guide</hi> they ſhould follow after he was taken from them.</p>
                  <p>That the Writers of the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> ſhould ſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently forewarn men of <hi>Hereticks, falſe Chriſts, falſe Prophets,</hi> and not once arme them againſt them, with
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:106321:24"/>letting them know this onely meanes of avoyding their danger.</p>
                  <p>That ſo great a part of the <hi>New Testament</hi> ſhould be employed againſt <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> and ſo little, indeed none at all, about the <hi>Vicar</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the <hi>Guide</hi> of the <hi>Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That our <hi>Saviour</hi> ſhould leave this onely means for the ending of <hi>Controverſie,</hi> and ſpeak ſo obſcurely and ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guouſly, that now our <hi>Judge</hi> is the greateſt <hi>controverſie,</hi> and the greateſt hindrance of ending them.</p>
                  <p>That there ſhould be better evidence in the <hi>Scripture</hi> to entitle the <hi>King</hi> to this <hi>Office,</hi> who diſclaims it, than the <hi>Pope</hi> who pretends it.</p>
                  <p>That St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſhould never exerciſe over the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> any one <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Juriſdiction,</hi> nor they ever give him any one <hi>title</hi> of <hi>Authority</hi> over them.</p>
                  <p>That if the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> did know that St. <hi>Peter</hi> was made <hi>head</hi> of them, when our <hi>Saviour</hi> ſaid, <hi>Thou art Peter,</hi> they ſhould ſtill contend who ſhould be the firſt; and that our <hi>Saviour</hi> ſhould not tell them, that <hi>Peter</hi> was the man.</p>
                  <p>That St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſhould ſay, He was in nothing inferior to the very chief <hi>Apoſtles.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That the <hi>Catechumeni</hi> in the <hi>primitive Church</hi> ſhould never be taught this <hi>foundation</hi> of their <hi>faith.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That the <hi>Fathers, Tertullian,</hi> St. <hi>Jerome</hi> and <hi>Optatus,</hi> when they flew higheſt in commendation of the <hi>Roman Church,</hi> ſhould attribute no more to her than to all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Apoſtolical Churches.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That in the <hi>controverſie</hi> about <hi>Eaſter,</hi> the <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Churches</hi> of <hi>Aſia</hi> ſhould be ſo ill catechiz'd, as not to know this <hi>principle</hi> of <hi>Religion, The neceſſity of conformity with the Church of</hi> Rome.</p>
                  <p>That they ſhould never be preſſed with any ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity in all things, but onely with the particular <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition</hi> of the <hi>Weſtern Churches</hi> in that point.</p>
                  <p>That <hi>Fryverus,</hi> and many other <hi>Biſhops</hi> (notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Ad hanc Eccleſiam neceſſe eſt omnem convenire Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiam,</hi>) ſhould not yet think that a neceſſary, nor a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:106321:24"/>ground of <hi>Excommunication,</hi> which the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> thought to be ſo.</p>
                  <p>That St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> and the <hi>Biſhops</hi> of <hi>Africk,</hi> ſhould be ſo ill inſtructed in their <hi>Faith,</hi> as not to know this <hi>Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation</hi> of it.</p>
                  <p>That they likewiſe, were never urged with any ſuch ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of <hi>Conformity</hi> with the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> nor char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with <hi>Hereſie</hi> or <hi>Error</hi> for denying it.</p>
                  <p>That when <hi>Liberius</hi> joyned in Communion with the <hi>Arrians,</hi> and ſubſcribed their <hi>Hereſie,</hi> the <hi>Arrians</hi> then ſhould not be the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Guide</hi> of <hi>Faith.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That never any <hi>Hereticks</hi> for <hi>five Ages</hi> after <hi>Chriſt</hi> were preſſed with this <hi>Argument of the Infallibility of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Church of Rome,</hi> or charged with the deniall of it, as a deteſtable <hi>Hereſie,</hi> for that <hi>Aeneas Silvius,</hi> ſhould have cauſe to ſay, <hi>Ante tempora Concilii Nicaeni quiſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ſibi vivebat, &amp; parvus reſpectus habebatur ad Eccleſiam Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That the <hi>Eccleſiaſticall ſtory</hi> of thoſe times mention no <hi>Acts</hi> of <hi>Authority</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> over other <hi>Churches,</hi> as if there ſhould be a <hi>Monarchy</hi> and <hi>Kings</hi> for ſome <hi>Ages</hi> together, and ſhould exerciſe no <hi>Acts</hi> of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction</hi> in it.</p>
                  <p>That to ſupply this defect, <hi>the Decretall Epiſtles</hi> ſhould be ſo impudently forged, which in a manner ſpeaks nothing but <hi>Reges &amp; Monarchas,</hi> I mean, <hi>The Popes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Lawes for, and exerciſing Authority over all other Churches.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That the <hi>Africane Churches</hi> in St. <hi>Auſtins</hi> time ſhould be ignorant that the <hi>Pope</hi> was <hi>Head</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> and <hi>Judge of Appeales, jure divino;</hi> and that there was a <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity</hi> of <hi>Conformity</hi> with the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> in this, and all other points of <hi>Doctrine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Nay, that the <hi>Popes</hi> themſelves ſhould be ſo ignorant of the true ground of this their <hi>Authority,</hi> as to pretend to it, not upon <hi>Scripture</hi> or <hi>univerſall Tradition,</hi> but upon an imaginary <hi>no-ſuch Canon</hi> of the <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Nice.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That <hi>Vincentius Lyrinenſis,</hi> ſeeking for a <hi>Guide</hi> of his
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:106321:25"/>
                     <hi>Faith,</hi> and a preſervation from <hi>Hereſie,</hi> ſhould be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of this ſo ready a one, <hi>The infallibility of the Church of Rome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>All theſe things, and many more, are very ſtrange to me, <hi>If the infallibility of the</hi> Roman <hi>Church be in deed, and was alwaies by Chriſtians acknowledged the Foundation of our Faith.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And therefore I beſeech you pardon me, if I chooſe to build mine upon one that is much firmer and ſafer, and lies open to none of thoſe <hi>Objections,</hi> which is <hi>Scripture and univerſall Tradition;</hi> and if one that is of this <hi>Faith</hi> may have leave to do ſo, I will ſubſcribe with hand and heart,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your very loving and true friend, W. C.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>By <hi>Bramhall,</hi> ſo you; my Lord Biſhop <hi>Bramhall,</hi> ſo I: when will you anſwer him, or rather reply to his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to <hi>Mounſeir Millitere?</hi> he is alive, and while he lives you dare not (I ſuppoſe) do it, ſince he Commands as much Learning and Reaſon as any of you all, put you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Hammond, Ferne, Tayler,</hi> ſo you, Doctor <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond,</hi> Doctor <hi>Ferne,</hi> Doctor <hi>Tayler,</hi> ſo I, (nor ſhould I have ſaid leſs of any of your <hi>Roman Doctors,</hi> ſo far have I read my Ethicks) are all living and can anſwer for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, with whom if you and yours hap to Cope, I am confident, you will fall in the Combate; if you Conquer I will be your <hi>Proſelite,</hi> not for the ſtrength of your Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, or pinning my Faith upon their Learning, Religion, Zeal, Sincerity, Vertue, and Wiſdom, (in all which they exceed) but for the ſtrictneſs of my own Conſcience, ſo that the Combate be decided before equitable, and equall Judges.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>30</label> 
            </p>
            <p>All this is demanded, ſuppoſing that the <hi>Roman</hi> Doctors were onely equall to thoſe of <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in all the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named Qualities, conducing to the perfect Authority of a Maſter in Chriſtianity.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:106321:25"/>
            <p>But now I demand, whether thoſe that have Authority of Teaching in the <hi>Roman Church</hi> generally ſpeaking in ſo much as can be prudently deduced by experience from them, are not much excelling the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Miniſtry in all the ſaid Qualities?</p>
            <p>What Councils have they worth the mentioning in compariſon of the <hi>Generall Councils</hi> conſenting with the preſent <hi>Roman</hi> Church, (even according to their own Confeſſion) as the ſecond of <hi>Nice,</hi> the Great Council of <hi>Lateran,</hi> the Councill of <hi>Conſtance, Florence</hi> and <hi>Trent,</hi> wherein ſuch multitudes of Learned men, and <hi>holy Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs, Metropolitans, Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Doctors, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates,</hi> both of the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> and <hi>Weſtern</hi> Churches, unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly confirmed the <hi>Roman</hi> and condemned the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant</hi> Doctrine?</p>
            <p>What proofes of Learning have the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, comparable to thoſe of the <hi>Roman Doctors,</hi> whereof many have written <hi>one,</hi> no ſmall number <hi>two,</hi> others <hi>three,</hi> and <hi>foure,</hi> others <hi>ſix, eight, ten, twelve,</hi> and ſome <hi>twenty,</hi> and <hi>four</hi> and <hi>twenty</hi> great Tomes in <hi>folio,</hi> and thoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleniſhed in the generall repute of Chriſtendom, even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt <hi>Proteſtants</hi> alſo, with profound and high Learning?</p>
            <p>Who amongſt their <hi>Miniſtry</hi> have they, who have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the univerſall eſteem of <hi>Sanctity,</hi> as hath our <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory, Beda, Thomas, Bonaventure, Antonine, Dominick,</hi> and diverſe others?</p>
            <p>Where find they amongſt theirs that zeal to paſs into the heart of ſo many barbarous and Heathen Nations to plant the Coſpel, even with the undergoing of unheard-of Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and ſuffering moſt cruel Martyrdoms, as many of the <hi>Roman</hi> Clergy have done within theſe late years?</p>
            <p>Let them name but any ſole <hi>Miniſter,</hi> who hath ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Martyrdom</hi> for preaching Chriſtian Faith to <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What means have the <hi>Proteſtant Miniſtery,</hi> with their Wives, Goods and Families, to apply themſelves to ſtudy and devotion, comparable to our ſingle Clergy and retired Religions?</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:106321:26"/>
            <p>Where is that <hi>unanimous conſent</hi> in all Points of <hi>Faith</hi> (ſeeing they are perpetually jarring, not onely one with another, but the ſame <hi>Miniſter</hi> diſſenting notoriouſly now from what they taught twenty years ago) amongſt them, compared to the conſtancy and agreement of our Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors?</p>
            <p>What <hi>Miracles</hi> have any of their Miniſtery done, in confirmation either of their <hi>Doctrine</hi> againſt the <hi>Roman Church,</hi> or of the <hi>Chriſtian Faith</hi> againſt <hi>Heathens,</hi> as (unleſs all human Faith be infringed) many of ours have done, both againſt them and Heathens?</p>
            <p>I could inſtance in many more particulars, but theſe may ſuffice for theſe ſhort demands, whence appears evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, That whoſoever profeſſes to be led by the ſole Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of <hi>Chriſtian Doctors</hi> and <hi>Paſtors,</hi> muſt either deſerve the eſteem, I ſay, not onely of an <hi>unchriſtian,</hi> but even of an imprudent man, if he adhere to ſo undeſerving and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible an Autho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ity, as is that of the <hi>Proteſtant Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry</hi> in compariſon of the <hi>Roman Doctors,</hi> who ſo incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parably outſtrip them, not onely in <hi>multitude,</hi> but in all the <hi>motives</hi> and <hi>perfections</hi> which give credit to the Authority of a Chriſtian Teacher.</p>
            <p>Again,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>30</label> at your <hi>incomparable compariſon,</hi> and with your addition of an <hi>undeſerving and contemptible Authority in the Proteſtant Miniſtery, outſtript in multitude, motives, and in all perfections:</hi> If this be your way to get credit to your cauſe, much good may it do you, but on an ordinary wiſe man I conceive it will not work. Had you continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed your ſuppoſition of Equality betwixt the <hi>Roman</hi> and <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Doctors, it would more become you, and might have proved a better way to overcome us; how much you excell us will preſently be ſeen in your demands.</p>
            <p>The firſt whereof is, What Councils have the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> worth the mentioning, in compariſon with the <hi>general Councils</hi> conſenting with the preſent <hi>Roman Church?</hi> and then you name <hi>five,</hi> the Second of <hi>Nice,</hi> the great Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Lateran,</hi> the Council of <hi>Conſtance, Florence</hi> and <hi>Trent,</hi> now I muſt marke a juggle here; you name not
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:106321:26"/>what you name theſe Councils for, but in the general, the particulars muſt be gueſt at, and I ſhall gueſs at them.</p>
            <p>The <hi>ſecond</hi> of <hi>Nice</hi> I conceive you name for Images, or worſhiping of God by Images, for untill this Council (which was not called untill the Year 787.) <hi>Images,</hi> or <hi>Worſhiping of God by Images</hi> was never decreed, and what value this Council is of, I tell you truely from my Books.</p>
            <p>There were more unlearned and evil-diſpoſed men in it, than ever were in any before, or almoſt ſince: it was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by <hi>Irene</hi> the <hi>Empreſs,</hi> an <hi>Heathen</hi> borne, converted <hi>Chriſtian</hi> by <hi>Conſtantinus</hi> his <hi>Father,</hi> to whom ſhe was married, and ſuffered her ſon <hi>Conſtantine</hi> to lofe his eyes, for withſtanding the determinations of this <hi>Council,</hi> ſo much natural affection ſhe had.</p>
            <p>Called by her, and managed by one <hi>Thariſius</hi> a Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, a Courtier, and Biſhop of one years ſtanding, and <hi>John Legate</hi> of the <hi>Eaſt Church,</hi> of whom it is ſaid, he was a devout man, but of no great Learning, and the other two that ruled the roſt in this <hi>Council</hi> were <hi>Theodoſius</hi> and <hi>Conſtantinus,</hi> of all whom together it hath been ſaid, There were never ſimpler men for gifts, nor worſe-diſpoſed men for attempts.</p>
            <p>And now againſt this Council againſt us, we <hi>oppoſe four</hi> Councils for us againſt you, The <hi>ſecond</hi> of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> the <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond</hi> of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> that of <hi>Eliberis,</hi> and the fourth of <hi>Carthage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The great Council of Lateran,</hi> I conceive it alledged for the matter of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> and here I note the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity</hi> of this <hi>Council;</hi> It was called in the Year 1215. ſo old is <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> no older, and againſt this we op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe all <hi>Councils</hi> and <hi>Fathers</hi> ſilence before, and before all, the inſtitution of Chriſt himſelf, who ſayes, <hi>The floſh profit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth no thing, my words are ſpirit,</hi> and the Expoſition of this Inſtitution of all Writers until this Council.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Council of Conſtance,</hi> I conceive it alledged <hi>for communion in one kind,</hi> againſt which I need not ſay more, than what <hi>Gelaſius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf ſaid, <hi>Sine grandi
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:106321:27"/>Sacrilegio fieri non poteſt,</hi> it was high Sacriledge to do it; unleſs you will give me leave to adde Chriſts own Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, <hi>Drink you all of this,</hi> all Laity as well as Clergy.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Florence,</hi> I conceive it alleadged for <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory,</hi> called <hi>Anno</hi> 1438. and if I am right in this <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecture,</hi> I need not ſay more then what <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>phonſus à Caſtro l.</hi> 8. <hi>adv. Hereſ. verbo, Indulgentia,</hi> hath ſaid, the mention of <hi>Purgatory in ancient writers is almoſt none at all;</hi> and if you will be pleaſed to name any one <hi>Father,</hi> ſave <hi>Origen, untill</hi> St. <hi>Gregory the Great</hi> his time, that is direct <hi>for Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory,</hi> I ſhall not much ſtand upon it, ſince I think it will not much hinder any mans Salvation, to believe it or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believe it: for my part I neither do, nor dare, nor will believe it.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Trent,</hi> called <hi>Anno</hi> 1563. I conceive it alleadged for all differences whatſoever betwixt the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> and <hi>Proteſtants;</hi> which <hi>Council,</hi> if you can prove was either <hi>lawfull, generall</hi> or <hi>free,</hi> which I yet poſitively deny in each, I ſhall ſit down; and in this <hi>Council</hi> I tell you, were not many <hi>Holy Patriarchs, Metropolitans, Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops, Biſhops,</hi> not one of the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Church, and you know the reaſon of it too.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For proofes of Learning,</hi> if the Church of <hi>England</hi> be not comparable to you in <hi>number,</hi> ſhe hath exceeded you <hi>in weight,</hi> and that this world knowes, and you have felt, and now you by your <hi>policy</hi> make the Churchmen of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> ſmart for it.</p>
            <p>For your univerſall eſteem of Sanctity, with your <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory, Beda, Thomas, Bonaventure, Antonine, Dominick,</hi> to avoide ſome ſtories of ſome of them, <hi>The Church</hi> of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> can produce as great a Cloud of witneſſes by the Verdict of all unbyaſſed men, in an <hi>Andrewes,</hi> a <hi>Buche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridge,</hi> a <hi>Laud,</hi> a <hi>Montague,</hi> a <hi>Hall,</hi> a <hi>Prideaux,</hi> and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe others before them, a <hi>Jewell,</hi> a <hi>Whitgift,</hi> a <hi>Cranmer,</hi> a <hi>Latimer,</hi> a <hi>Ridley.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Speak not too much of your zelous paſſing into barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Nations, to convert them, leſt the <hi>Indean</hi> be brought out of Love with <hi>Heaven,</hi> if the <hi>Roman</hi> go thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:106321:27"/>
            <p>And for our <hi>Miniſtry</hi> with their <hi>Wives,</hi> (<hi>Goods</hi> and <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies,</hi> we have little left, thanks to you, or ſome as bad as you) they can apply themſelves to Study, and Devotion, as well and with leſs ſin, then your ſingle Clergy, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired Religions.</p>
            <p>Boaſt not too much of your <hi>unanimous conſent,</hi> untill your <hi>Dominicans,</hi> and <hi>Franciſcans</hi> be at peace, about the <hi>imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culate Conception</hi> of the <hi>bleſſed Virgin,</hi> untill your <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> and <hi>Dominicans</hi> be at peace about the <hi>Aids,</hi> and <hi>Operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Grace,</hi> untill <hi>Bannes</hi> and <hi>Leſſius</hi> be at peace in the ſad point of abſolute Reprobation; untill your <hi>Doctors</hi> of <hi>Sorbon</hi> and <hi>Lovaine</hi> be at peace about the <hi>Popes Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy;</hi> untill <hi>Venice</hi> and <hi>Rome</hi> be all at peace about the <hi>Popes power;</hi> untill the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Spaniſh Papiſts</hi> be at peace about an <hi>equality of Subjection to the Pope;</hi> untill <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>regory</hi> the firſt, and <hi>Gregory</hi> the <hi>ſeventh</hi> be by ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> your ſelves reconciled about the Title of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſalis Epiſcopus;</hi> untill all of you be reconciled about the <hi>Popes infallibility;</hi> untill all and every one of you tell the world, whether <hi>Tranſlation of the Bible</hi> by <hi>Sextus the firſt,</hi> or <hi>Clement the eight</hi> be the beſt; <hi>cum multis aliis quae nunc perſcribere longum eſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For miracles to confirm our Doctrine againſt yours,</hi> we need none, untill you by a <hi>new miracle</hi> turne <hi>Rome</hi> as it is, into <hi>Rome</hi> as it was; and then we all meet in an <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable Authority of one Catholick Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whether hence be not evidently diſcovered not onely the <hi>inſufferable Pride of Luther,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>31</label> and the other <hi>Originall beginners,</hi> of any <hi>Sect in Proteſtancy</hi> in preferring their ſole <hi>Authority</hi> before that of the <hi>Prelates</hi> and <hi>Doctors,</hi> of all the viſible Churches in Chriſtendom exiſtent, when they begun firſt to preach their Doctrine, but the <hi>extreme madneſs</hi> of all the <hi>ignorant Laity,</hi> who followed them, upon their ſole <hi>Authority,</hi> and preferred one ſingle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon upon his bare word, (without any extraordinary ſignes or manifeſt proofes from Heaven, atteſting his Authority) before all the <hi>Doctors, Prelates, Councils, Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,</hi> within the precincts of Chriſtendom; both of that
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:106321:28"/>preſent time, and for 900. years before? And if thoſe were infected with ſo deep a frenſie, how can any man be adjudged deſervedly diſcreet and prudent, who approves of their proceedings in this particular, and ſides with them, (at leaſt in ſome Article of other) in the oppoſition of the whole Chriſtian world, as all <hi>Proteſtants</hi> do, even to this day?</p>
            <p>Rarely ſpoken,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>31</label> and a fair way to catch birds, <hi>The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufferable Pride of Luther;</hi> if he were guilty of it, let him anſwer for it, <hi>and all other Originall beginners of any Sect in Proteſtancy;</hi> Sir, it is very well known who ſaid, <hi>This Sect is every where ſpoken againſt,</hi> yet for all that, that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Sect over-ſpread it ſelf, and conquered the whole world, and this very Sect of <hi>Proteſtancy,</hi> hath put a fair beginning to the Conqueſt of the <hi>Roman Doctrine;</hi> which though now like that <hi>Sect</hi> under <hi>the ten Perſecutio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> ſomewhat eclipſed, hath yet ſo much light left, as to diſcerne between <hi>all the viſible</hi> Churches in Chriſtendom, all <hi>Doctors, Prelates, Councils, Churches, within the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cincts of Chriſtendom,</hi> and the preſent <hi>Roman,</hi> and claim none for our beginners but <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apostles,</hi> the four <hi>Generall Councils</hi> and the <hi>Primitive Fathers,</hi> and the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf as it was, when it was <hi>Catholick;</hi> and therefore think they are to be judged deſervedly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet and prudent, who approve our preſent <hi>Doctrines,</hi> with the whole <hi>Chriſtian world,</hi> and deſert the preſent <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence I farther demand,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>32</label> That ſeeing on one ſide <hi>the true Chriſtian Religion,</hi> having the <hi>divine Wiſdom</hi> for its <hi>Authority,</hi> cannot admit of any thing imprudent as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly belonging to it, in the choyce of it; and on the other ſide, That the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> or any <hi>Sect</hi> whatſoever ſprung from it, or exiſtent in it, cannot be prudently cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen by any unlearned perſon, who is ſufficiently informed of the nullity of that <hi>Authority,</hi> which propounds it, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with the Authority, propounding the <hi>Roman Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion;</hi> whether, I ſay, thoſe particulars conſidered, the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant Religion</hi> in any Sect of it whatſoever can be eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the true <hi>Chriſtian Religion?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:106321:28"/>
            <p>Sir,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>32</label> I have not yet known the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into any <hi>Sects;</hi> we all believe the ſame <hi>Creeds,</hi> we all hold the ſame <hi>foundation</hi> and <hi>Articles of Faith,</hi> we all hold the <hi>Scriptures</hi> the onely judge of <hi>controverſies,</hi> which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you deny and decline, we think that man <hi>imprudent</hi> who deſerts the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> to turn <hi>Roman,</hi> and him <hi>prudent</hi> that deſerts the <hi>Roman</hi> to turn <hi>Proteſtant;</hi> ſince there is but a poſſibility of ſalvation for an unlearned man in the <hi>Roman,</hi> becauſe it depends upon <hi>human Authority;</hi> in the <hi>Protestant there is a certainty of ſalvation for unlearned and learned,</hi> becauſe it depends upon <hi>divine Authority,</hi> and therefore a <hi>true chriſtian Church and Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence I preſs further,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>32</label> Whether the proving that <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion</hi> cannot be <hi>prudently</hi> choſen or retained by any <hi>unlearned perſons,</hi> who are ſufficiently informed of the eminent <hi>Authority</hi> propounding the <hi>Roman Religion,</hi> is not a ſufficient Argument to them, that no <hi>Sect</hi> amongſt them, in any point wherein it differs from the <hi>Roman,</hi> hath either any ſolid ground in the Holy <hi>Scriptu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es,</hi> or true relation to Gods <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> or coherence with <hi>true Religion,</hi> ſeeing a Religion which cannot by them be pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently choſen, cannot poſſibly proceed from any of theſe <hi>three,</hi> whatſoever fair ſhew <hi>Protestants</hi> (each reſpectively to his ſeveral <hi>Sect</hi>) make vainly of them?</p>
            <p>Sir, all theſe are but words,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>33</label> and you do ſtill <hi>ſupponere</hi> not <hi>ſupponenda:</hi> For that Religion may be prudently cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, whoſe rule of Faith is certain; but ſuch is the rule of Faith in the <hi>Protestant Religion</hi> (as being ultimated and determined in and by the Scripture) therefore the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion</hi> may be prudently choſen. Again, that Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion cannot be prudently choſen, whoſe Authority, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing it, is not ſufficient; but ſuch is the Authority, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding the preſent <hi>Roman</hi> Religion (as being <hi>human</hi> whether <hi>Pope</hi> or Council) therefore the <hi>Roman</hi> preſent Religion cannot prudently be choſen.</p>
            <p>Again, that Religion may prudently be choſen, which hath true relation to <hi>Gods Holy Spirit,</hi> but the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion hath ſuch relation, therefore the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:106321:29"/>may prudently be choſen; for there is a true relation betwixt <hi>Gods Holy Spirit</hi> and Gods Holy Word, becauſe <hi>Gods Holy Spirit</hi> is the Author of <hi>Gods Holy Word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I need not ſpeak of the <hi>third,</hi> becauſe <hi>coherence with true reaſon</hi> follows either of the former.</p>
            <p>And upon this I demand yet further,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>34</label> Whether the <hi>Roman Doctors</hi> have any obligation to urge any other Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument then this, either from <hi>Scripture, Fathers</hi> or <hi>reaſon, againſt Proteſtants,</hi> till they have cleared their <hi>Religion</hi> from the impeachment of <hi>imprudence,</hi> committed by their followers in the election of it, or perſiſting in it, as is afore declared?</p>
            <p>Sir,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>34</label> 
               <hi>your afore Declaration</hi> hath proved little, and your preſent proves leſs, though I confeſs your <hi>Roman Doctors</hi> have no farther obligation to urge any other Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment then <hi>Scripture, Fathers,</hi> or <hi>Reaſon,</hi> againſt <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Urge either of them to purpoſe, and we ſhall be ſo far from clearing our Religion from the impeachment of <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prudence,</hi> that we will confeſs, it is the onely <hi>prudence</hi> in the choyce of Religion, to embrace the <hi>Roman.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Till then, I ſay,</p>
            <p>That Religion which hath not hitherto been convinced from <hi>Scriptures, Fathers</hi> or <hi>Reaſon,</hi> ought by the <hi>rule of prudence</hi> to be embraced; but ſuch is the <hi>Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> therefore by the <hi>rule of prudence,</hi> the Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion ought to be embraced; or if you will have it, <hi>per con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traria,</hi> take it thus:</p>
            <p>It is a part of <hi>imprudence</hi> to embrace that Religion, which hath been convinced from <hi>Scriptures, Fathers,</hi> and Reaſon; but ſuch is the <hi>Roman Religion,</hi> therefore it is the part of imprudence to embrace the Roman Religion.</p>
            <p>Now Sir, to avoid reply, give me leave to tell you, <hi>Baptizing as Chriſt hath Commanded, Praying as Chriſt hath taught, Believing the Scriptures, Serving and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping God without Images, Receiving the Sacrament as Chriſt Inſtituted it,</hi> have not been convinced by <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, Fathers</hi> or <hi>Reaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:106321:29"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Equalling Tradition to Scripture, Worſhiping of Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, or God by Images, Praying to Saints, Receiving the Sacrament in one kind, believing the Popes infallibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, &amp;c.</hi> have been convinced by <hi>Scriptures, Fathers</hi> and <hi>Reaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the contrary ſide, I demand,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>35</label> whether the <hi>Roman Doctors</hi> have any obligation in rigour of diſpute, to uſe any other Argument for perſwading unlearned perſons to deſert the <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> and embrace the <hi>Roman Religion,</hi> then this imprudence, in adhering to the <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> and of <hi>prudence,</hi> in uniting themſelves to the <hi>Roman Church,</hi> ſo long as the ſaid <hi>unlearned Proteſtants</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade themſelves, that they proceed prudently, in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring their own before the <hi>Roman;</hi> ſeeing this erroneous perſwaſion is the firſt ſtep which muſt be redreſſed in relinquiſhing the one, and the contrary perſwaſion the firſt ſtep which muſt be fixed in approaching to the other.</p>
            <p>Now when <hi>unlearned Proteſtants</hi> once confeſſe that they are convinced in this, and thereupon recede from <hi>Proteſtancy,</hi> but object, that the prudentiall Motives to prefer the <hi>Roman Religion</hi> before the <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> as they conceive that the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> is wholly improbable, and ſo to be deſerted, ſo they convince no more, then that the <hi>Roman</hi> is probable, and ſo it is great Likelyhood to be the true <hi>Religion,</hi> but convince not, that it is ſo much as morally certaine. To Proteſtants brought thus farre, there is an obligation put upon the <hi>Roman Doctors,</hi> to prove at leaſt the morall certainty of it, to ſuch as ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that it is <hi>morally certaine,</hi> that the <hi>Roman Re-Religion</hi> is <hi>the ſole true ſaving Religion,</hi> but deny not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that it thereby followes, that it is <hi>infallibly certain,</hi> riſes an Obligation to prove, that it is <hi>Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly certain;</hi> and when one is once convinced of this alſo, but yet doubts, whether this <hi>Infallibility</hi> be Divine, and ſo the higheſt of all <hi>Infallibilities,</hi> there will be alſo an Obligation to ſhew to ſuch as are brought on ſo far,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:106321:30"/>
               <hi>the moſt high divine infallibility of the Roman Religion;</hi> hence therefore I demand, whether our late <hi>Proteſtants</hi> and <hi>Socinians</hi> proceed not prepoſterouſly and unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, in preſſing <hi>Roman Doctors</hi> to demonſtrate the <hi>Divine Infallibility of the truth of the</hi> Roman <hi>Religion,</hi> before they themſelves grant, that it is <hi>infallible</hi> in any degree, or <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally certain,</hi> or <hi>probable,</hi> or <hi>prudential?</hi> for though it be neceſſary to prove all theſe particulars in their due cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, yet there is no neceſſity to prove them all at once to every Adverſary, but by degrees, the one in order after the other, with correſpondence to what of them is denyed, or called in queſtion by thoſe with whom we treat; for thus we proceed <hi>orderly</hi> and <hi>logically, à notiori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ad ignotiora,</hi> and hold a correſpondence with <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> by proceeding <hi>ab imperfectioribus ad perfectiora,</hi> ſtill obſerving the ſtep or progreſs of our <hi>Adverſary,</hi> and ſtill ſtepping and going along with him; and if this <hi>method</hi> had been ſtrictly held by our late <hi>controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts,</hi> the <hi>Adverſaries</hi> mouths had been ſtopped long before this.</p>
            <p>Sir,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>35</label> what would you be at? whither would you go? You have yet gained no <hi>imprudence</hi> upon the unlearned, either to embrace the <hi>Roman,</hi> or deſert the <hi>Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> and therefore ſome obligation lies upon your <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Doctors,</hi> without rigor of Diſpute, to uſe ſome other Argument than this:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But this is an erroneous perſwaſion in the unlearned Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants;</hi> and as the firſt ſtep muſt be removed, <hi>for relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhing their own and embracing your Religion; and then you will uſe another Argument to convince, that the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion is wholly improbable, and then you will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, that the Proteſtant Religion is not ſo much as morally cortain, but your own is; and then you will prove, that it is the ſole true ſaving Religion, and then that it is infallibly cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and last of all, that your Roman Religion is the moſt divine, infallible, certain Religion;</hi> and all this to follow <hi>Logick</hi> and <hi>Nature from things known to things unknown,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:106321:30"/>from things imperfect to things perfect:</hi> But firſt of all the poor <hi>unlearned Protestant</hi> muſt deny his own <hi>Religion</hi> to be either <hi>prudential,</hi> or <hi>probable,</hi> or <hi>morally certain,</hi> or <hi>infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libly certain or divine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nunc lupum auribus teneo;</hi> juſt ſo the <hi>Wolfe</hi> would have dealt with the <hi>Lambe,</hi> to part with his Protector, and then the <hi>innocent Lambe</hi> ſhould know that he had no better friend then the <hi>Wolfe;</hi> I will deal more <hi>Lambe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like</hi> with you; prove either, or all of theſe, either <hi>Pro,</hi> or <hi>Con,</hi> for the <hi>Roman,</hi> or againſt the <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> and you will be taken for an excellent <hi>Logician,</hi> and a good Naturaliſt, but till then for a <hi>poor Divine,</hi> ſince your whole courſe and diſcourſe hitherto hath been but <hi>Petitio principii,</hi> and not able to ſtop your <hi>Adverſaries</hi> mouthes, though you ſpeak aloud, till then I ſay but this much,</p>
            <p>That Religion is moſt prudently to be choſen which hath <hi>probable, Morall, Infallible</hi> Divine certainty in it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But ſuch is the</hi> Proteſtant <hi>Religion,</hi> becauſe it is <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably, Morally, Infallibly,</hi> and <hi>Divinely</hi> certain by the Authority of Fathers, <hi>of the Councils, and of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore the</hi> Proteſtant <hi>Religion</hi> is moſt prudently to be choſen, becauſe the <hi>Fathers, Councils,</hi> and <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> aſſert all their <hi>Affirmative Tenents.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seeing theſe demands are propoſed to ſuch as believe,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>36</label> that without <hi>true Chriſtian Faith</hi> no man can be ſaved, and that this <hi>ſaving Faith</hi> is one onely, and that this <hi>onely Faith</hi> is <hi>Infallible,</hi> and <hi>Divine;</hi> and moreover ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is already ſhewed, that every difference in any point of <hi>Faith</hi> whatſoever, makes <hi>a different Faith and Religion,</hi> and that amongſt all the <hi>different Religions and Beliefs</hi> now on foot in theſe parts of Chriſtendom, there is none that can be prudently embraced (by ſuch as are in the number of the <hi>unlearned,</hi> and yet are ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently informed about the force of the Authority of
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:106321:31"/>thoſe who teach them) ſave the <hi>Roman,</hi> and that no Religion can be true which cannot be prudently em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced by ſuch <hi>unlearned perſons,</hi> ſeeing in a manner the whole multitude of Chriſtians conſiſts of thoſe who are <hi>unlearned;</hi> and muſt according to prudence follow the <hi>Authority</hi> of their <hi>Teachers;</hi> thoſe things I ſay, conſidered, it is finally demanded, whether by proving that the <hi>Roman Faith</hi> onely can be prudently embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced (which is already done) it is not made inevita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly cleare, that the <hi>Roman onely</hi> is that <hi>Divine, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible,</hi> one true <hi>Faith,</hi> wherein Chriſtians may be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved?</p>
            <p>Sir,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>36</label> thoſe things have been conſidered, and yet you have not proved, that the <hi>Roman Faith onely can be prudently embraced,</hi> though you ſay, <hi>it is already done,</hi> (for it is already undone) and therefore it is not <hi>inevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably</hi> cleare, that the Roman onely is that <hi>Divine, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible one</hi> true <hi>Faith</hi> wherein Chriſtians may be ſaved. For,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That Faith onely is not Divine,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> which is built upon <hi>Tradition,</hi> becauſe <hi>Tradition</hi> is but <hi>Humane,</hi> but the <hi>Roman Faith</hi> is built upon <hi>Tradition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore the <hi>Roman Faith onely</hi> is not that <hi>Divine Faith</hi> wherein Chriſtians can be ſaved.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That Faith onely</hi> is not <hi>infallible,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> which is grounded upon the <hi>Authority of men,</hi> whether <hi>Pope</hi> or <hi>Council,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>Authority of men,</hi> whether <hi>Pope</hi> or <hi>Council,</hi> is <hi>fallible.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſuch is the <hi>Roman Faith,</hi> becauſe <hi>Virtually</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved into the <hi>Pope,</hi> who cannot erre, ſay ſome of the <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> and <hi>Repreſentatively</hi> into a <hi>Councill,</hi> which cannot erre, ſay other of the <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> but both one and the other <hi>erroneouſly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore the <hi>Roman Faith onely</hi> is not that <hi>infallible faith</hi> wherein <hi>Chriſtians</hi> may be ſaved.</p>
            <p>That Faith onely is not the <hi>One,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> which hath o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Articles</hi> added to it, then what the <hi>Apostles
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:106321:31"/>faith,</hi> the <hi>Nicene faith,</hi> the <hi>Athanaſian faith</hi> containe.</p>
            <p>But ſuch is the <hi>Roman faith,</hi> becauſe <hi>the faith of Rome,</hi> in the <hi>Council of Trent,</hi> hath added the <hi>Articles</hi> of <hi>Purgatory, of the Prieſts intention in Baptiſm, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore the <hi>Roman faith onely</hi> is not the <hi>one faith</hi> wherein Chriſtians may be ſaved.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That faith is not the true faith,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> wherein the <hi>profeſſors</hi> dare not as well dye as live; but ſuch is the <hi>Roman faith,</hi> becauſe in their Life they rely upon, and preach their owne <hi>merits,</hi> but at their death rely onely upon the mercies of <hi>God</hi> in the <hi>merits of Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> in which <hi>divine, infallible, one true faith,</hi> that you and all <hi>Chriſtians</hi> with my ſelf may meet, is the hearty deſire of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
               <signed>Your Friend and Servant, <hi>T. SWADLIN.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
